<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="23.08.0">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="0" size="6" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="10" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="6" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="10" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="10" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="8" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">1 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="244" width="102" height="13" font="1"><b>REPORT Nº 90/06</b></text>
<text top="55" left="346" width="5" height="9" font="2"><a href="etree.html#1"><b>1</b></a></text>
<text top="725" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">5. The Inter-American Commission assigned number 731-03 to the petition and, on December </text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">24, 2003, requested information from the Salvadoran State about the parties involved in the </text>
<text top="56" left="351" width="4" height="13" font="3"><a href="etree.html#1"> </a></text>
<text top="69" left="253" width="92" height="13" font="3">PETITION 731-03 </text>
<text top="81" left="258" width="82" height="13" font="3">ADMISSIBILITY </text>
<text top="93" left="206" width="186" height="13" font="3">JOSE ADRIAN ROCHAC HERNANDEZ </text>
<text top="105" left="262" width="74" height="13" font="3">EL SALVADOR </text>
<text top="117" left="253" width="92" height="13" font="3">October 21, 2006 </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="13" height="13" font="1"><b>I. </b></text>
<text top="154" left="92" width="64" height="13" font="1"><b>SUMMARY  </b></text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">1. On September 11, 2003, The Inter-American Commission on Human Rights (hereinafter the </text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">“Inter-American Commission” or “the IACHR”) received a complaint filed by the Association for </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="482" height="13" font="3">the Search of Missing Children (<i>Asociación Pro-Búsqueda de Niñas y Niños Desaparecidos—</i></text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="4"><i>Asociación Pro-Búsqueda</i>) (hereinafter “the petitioners”), claiming that the Republic of El </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="493" height="13" font="3">Salvador (hereinafter “the State”) bears international responsibility for the forced </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">disappearance of the child José Adrián Rochac Hernández  and for the subsequent failure to </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">investigate, and make reparations for these alleged violations. The petitioners claim that the </text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">reported incident constitutes a violation of several rights enshrined in the American Convention </text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">on Human Rights (hereinafter &#34;the Inter-American Convention&#34;): the right to personal integrity </text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">(Article 5); the right to personal liberty (Article 7); the right to a fair trial (Article 8); the right to </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">protect the family (Article 17); the right to a name (Article 18); the rights of the child (Article </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">19); and the right to judicial protection (Article 25), all in violation of the general duty to respect </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="173" height="13" font="3">and guarantee rights (Article 1.1). </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">2. The complaint alleges that, on December 12, 1980, José Adrián Rochac Hernández, age five, </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">was taken by military personnel belonging to El Salvador’s Air Force and members of </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">paramilitary groups from the zone of San Martín, during a raid in the canton of San José </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">Segundo, district of San Martín, in the department of San Salvador. Since then, almost 25 </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">years after the incident, the whereabouts of the child are unknown. All the steps taken with </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the authorities to shed light on the incident, including the filing of a criminal complaint and a </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="387" height="13" font="3">motion for the issuance of a writ of habeas corpus, have been unsuccessful. </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="445" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">3. The State contends that remedies under domestic law have not been exhausted. The State </text>
<text top="457" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">points out that the Attorney General’s Office started investigating the case and that this </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">investigation is ongoing and must be delved into further to determine the circumstances of the </text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">case. The State also points out that the motion for a writ of habeas corpus was filed 20 years </text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">after the incident occurred and that it was dismissed for lack of background records proving </text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="491" height="13" font="3">disappearance. It also claims that, during the domestic armed conflict, there were </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">opportunities to file a report on the disappearance to the Government Commission on Human </text>
<text top="530" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">Rights  and the International Committee of the Red Cross, but that, regarding the child, this </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">was never done. Therefore, it requests the IACHR to declare the petition inadmissible for </text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">failure to exhaust remedies under domestic law. Furthermore, the State points out that the </text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">IACHR lacks jurisdiction because the law applicable during the armed conflict was International </text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">Humanitarian Law and that the Inter-American Court of Human Rights lacks jurisdiction to </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">hear the case because of the reservations made by the State of El Salvador when it accepted </text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="183" height="13" font="3">the Court’s contentious jurisdiction. </text>
<text top="615" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">4. Without prejudging the merits of the case, the IACHR concludes in this report that the case </text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">is admissible, since it meets the requirements set forth in Articles 46 and 47 of the American </text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">Convention. The Inter-American Commission decides to notify the parties of its decision and to </text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">continue the in-depth examination of the supposed violations of the American Convention, </text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="435" height="13" font="3">publish this decision and include it in its Annual Report to the OAS General Assembly. </text>
<text top="688" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="700" left="57" width="18" height="13" font="1"><b>II. </b></text>
<text top="700" left="92" width="218" height="13" font="1"><b>PROCESSING WITH THE COMMISSION </b></text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="751" left="57" width="148" height="13" font="3">                                           </text>
<text top="762" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">1</text>
<text top="765" left="61" width="481" height="11" font="5"> Commissioner Florentín Meléndez, a national of El Salvador, did not participate in the deliberations or voting on the </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="338" height="11" font="5">present case, in compliance with Article 17.2.a of the IACHR’s Rules of Procedures. </text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="6" size="11" family="RIFWNG+Univers" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="7" size="12" family="TimesNewRomanPSMT" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="8" size="9" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">2 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">complaint. The State responded on March 5, 2004. On April 22, 2004, the petitioners </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">submitted their observations on the information from the State, and the State responded on </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="279" height="13" font="3">February 15, 2005 by submitting further observations. </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="200" height="13" font="1"><b>III.  POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES </b></text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="15" height="13" font="1"><b>A. </b></text>
<text top="129" left="92" width="85" height="13" font="1"><b>The petitioners</b></text>
<text top="129" left="177" width="4" height="14" font="6"><b> </b></text>
<text top="144" left="57" width="3" height="11" font="7"> </text>
<text top="155" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">6. The complaint received by the IACHR alleges that José  Adrián Rochac Hernández was the </text>
<text top="167" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">victim of a forced disappearance, presumably at the hands of members of the Armed Forces of El </text>
<text top="180" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Salvador and members of paramilitary groups from the zone of San Martín. The petitioners claim </text>
<text top="192" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">that this case pertains to a pattern of disappearance of children during the armed conflict. </text>
<text top="204" left="57" width="335" height="13" font="3">Regarding the facts of the case, the petitioners state the following: </text>
<text top="216" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="228" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">On December 12, 1980, at about nine o’clock in the morning, a military raid took place in the canton of </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">San José Segundo of the Municipality of San Martín; the raid was comprised of paramilitary forces from </text>
<text top="250" left="57" width="487" height="12" font="8">the zone of San Martín and troops of the Armed Forces of El Salvador (FAES) under the command of </text>
<text top="261" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">General Rafael Bustillo. The Hernández Rochac family lived in the canton of San José Segundo. At that </text>
<text top="272" left="57" width="488" height="12" font="8">time, the household was comprised of Mrs. María Silverio Rochac, age 38, her six children, Sergio </text>
<text top="283" left="57" width="487" height="12" font="8">Antonio, age 12; María Juliana, age 10; María Del Tránsito, age 8; José Adrián Rochac, age 5; Ana </text>
<text top="294" left="57" width="487" height="12" font="8">Margarita, age 3; and a newborn child Nicolás Alfonso, age 6 days, all bearing the surname Rochac </text>
<text top="305" left="57" width="55" height="12" font="8">Hernández. </text>
<text top="316" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="328" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">For their safety and in view of the raid that was taking place, the Rochac Hernández family decided to </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">lock the doors of its house. The soldiers and paramilitary forces who were members of the raid reached </text>
<text top="350" left="57" width="488" height="12" font="8">the house of the Rochac Hernández family, broke down the doors and asked for weapons, they </text>
<text top="361" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">immediately hit Mrs. María Silverio and afterwards they took her out of the house, and the child Sergio </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="8">Antonio, who was very attached to his mother, went outside with her. They were both taken at about 30 </text>
<text top="382" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="8">meters away from the house, where they were shot and killed instantly. Afterwards the military withdrew </text>
<text top="393" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">from the place, taking with them the child José Adrián, and the three sisters and six-day-old child were </text>
<text top="404" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">left alone. The soldiers and paramilitary troops went in the direction of San Bartolomé Perulapía; near </text>
<text top="415" left="57" width="454" height="12" font="8">Santa Elena, which is on the highway to Suchitoto, there were army trucks waiting for the soldiers. </text>
<text top="426" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="8"> </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="8">At about five meters away from the house of the Rochac Hernández family, there was Mrs. Dolores López </text>
<text top="448" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">Beltrán, who saw the child José Adrián Rochac Hernández, who appeared distraught, taken away by the </text>
<text top="459" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">soldiers of the Salvadoran Armed Forces. Nearby, where the Army trucks were waiting, on the edge of </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">the highway, Mrs. Jesús Beltrán (deceased) lived as a displaced person, and she saw the child; she knew </text>
<text top="481" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="8">him because he was a distant relative; she later saw him when he was lifted into one of the trucks. Since </text>
<text top="492" left="57" width="487" height="12" font="8">then, his whereabouts have been unknown. One of the persons involved both in the raid and in the </text>
<text top="503" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">accusations made against the Rochac Hernández family was Mr. Rodolfo López Miranda (deceased), who </text>
<text top="514" left="57" width="309" height="12" font="8">at that time was a member of the paramilitary corps of San Martín. </text>
<text top="525" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="537" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">7. The petitioners allege that in El Salvador there are no effective remedies to find children </text>
<text top="549" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">reported missing during the armed conflict. They point out that, during the war, the relatives of </text>
<text top="561" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the alleged victims did not resort to reporting violations because many families kept away from </text>
<text top="573" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">military raids and also for fear that, if they reported incidents, the authorities would suspect </text>
<text top="585" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">them of collaborating with the guerrilla. Therefore, during this period, there were no viable </text>
<text top="598" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">remedies. Afterwards, the amnesty law enacted in 1993 made it impossible to enforce the </text>
<text top="610" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">recommendations of the Truth Commission regarding the investigation of human rights </text>
<text top="622" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">violations. Finally, they indicate that the writ of habeas corpus, which should be adequate for </text>
<text top="634" left="57" width="306" height="13" font="3">cases of forced disappearance, is not effective in El Salvador. </text>
<text top="646" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="658" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">8. Despite the above, the petitioners point out that they have resorted to various proceedings, </text>
<text top="671" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">which have been ineffective and insufficient. On May 29, 1996, the child’s father, Mr.  Alfonso </text>
<text top="683" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Hernández Herrera, went to the <i>Asociación Pro-Búsqueda,</i> and on May 31, 1996, turned to the </text>
<text top="695" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">Public Prosecutor’s Office for the Defense of Human Rights. Likewise, on April 10, 2002, Mr. </text>
<text top="707" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Alfonso Hernández Herrera, filed a formal request for the investigation of the whereabouts of </text>
<text top="719" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">his son José Adrián Rochac, with the Soyapango Subregional Office of the Attorney General’s </text>
<text top="731" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Office. Because he received no response, on October 16, 2002, Mr. Alfonso Hernández Herrera </text>
<text top="743" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">filed a motion for the issuance of a writ of habeas corpus with the Constitutional Law Chamber </text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="167" height="13" font="3">of the Supreme Court of Justice. </text>
<text top="768" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">3 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">9. It is noted that it was not possible to file the report before 1996 because, as a result of the </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">armed conflict prevailing at the time, there was fear that any person who showed up personally </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">at military headquarters would be suspected of having ties with the guerrilla and would be the </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">target of reprisals. Regarding this, the Truth Commission for El Salvador cautioned that many </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">human rights violations were committed against the civilian population merely on the suspicion </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">that they were collaborating with the guerrilla forces, as part of the campaign, especially during </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">the early years of the conflict, aimed at “draining the pond to catch the fish.” In this </text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">environment, the petitioners claim there was no trust in authorities, especially when the human </text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">rights violations were perpetrated by the Salvadoran Army. The petitioners further state that, in </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">addition to fear, it was also physically impossible to go to the courts and that the authorities did </text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="244" height="13" font="3">not have the capacity to process the complaints. </text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">10.The petitioners point out that the Attorney General’s investigation, undertaken as a result </text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">of the report made on April 10, 2002, has not been effective. Since the report was filed, the </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">petitioners note that the Attorney General’s Office has only requested information about the </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">case from  <i>Pro-Búsqueda</i>  and has inspected the site of the crime. The petitioners claim that </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">they have not obtained any further information about the proceedings to date, despite the </text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">submittal of three requests. The petitioners claim that the Attorney General’s Office has not </text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">made the necessary efforts to investigate the case as there are other steps that could be taken </text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">to gather further information on the facts, and these steps have not been taken. They also </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="407" height="13" font="3">note that the respective injunction has not been filed with the competent Court. </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">11.The petitioners contend that the motion for the issuance of a writ of habeas corpus, filed on </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">October 16, 2002, because of the ineffectiveness of the criminal investigation, has not been </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">successful in finding José Adrián Rochac. Indeed, in the ruling of March 3, 2003, the Court </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">dismissed the motion, claiming that the petitioners had failed to submit a minimum number of </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">elements that might lead the Chamber to admit the likelihood of the alleged forced </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="457" height="13" font="3">disappearance, without having conducted any kind of inquiry that it was authorized to do. </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">12.In short, the petitioners claim that, in El Salvador, there is no adequate or effective remedy </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">to find children who had disappeared during the armed conflict in El Salvador. They point out </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">that until not long ago, before the establishment of the Truth Commission, in El Salvador there </text>
<text top="445" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">was no chance for petitioners to gain access to any domestic judicial remedy. Since then, the </text>
<text top="457" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">petitioners claim that the domestic remedies available in El Salvador have been ineffectual in </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">investigating the facts, determining the whereabouts of  José Adrián Rochac Hernández or </text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">making reparations for the consequences of the alleged violations. In this regard, they argue </text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">that more than 10 years have elapsed since the case was reported for the first time, and in that </text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">time the State’s response has been grossly negligent and desultory, although the facts </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">characterize the incident as a public crime. The petitioners therefore request application of the </text>
<text top="530" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">exception to the rule requiring exhaustion of domestic remedies as provided for in Article 46.2.b </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="95" height="13" font="3">of the Convention. </text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">13.Regarding applicable rules, the petitioners contend that the Salvadoran State ratified the </text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">American Convention on June 23, 1978 and is therefore held liable by the Convention for the </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="229" height="13" font="3">harm done to José Adrián Rochac Hernández. </text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="615" left="57" width="15" height="13" font="1"><b>B. </b></text>
<text top="615" left="92" width="57" height="13" font="1"><b>The State </b></text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">14.The Salvadoran State states that, during the period of the armed conflict, there was no </text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">pattern of forced disappearance of persons, including children, but rather that the armed </text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">conflict itself engendered situations where families were involuntarily separated; therefore, in </text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">many cases, the consequences and scope of said separation were unknown. It adds that, </text>
<text top="688" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">during the conflict, there were certain territories controlled by the Farabundo Martí National </text>
<text top="700" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Liberation Front (Frente Farabundo Martí para la Liberación Nacional—FMLN), where the latter </text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">depended on the “masses” or campesino population who lived with the guerrilla or contributed </text>
<text top="725" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">to its subsistence. The State further adds that the raids conducted by the Armed Forces were </text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">not intended to eliminate this civilian population who voluntarily went along with the guerrilla, </text>
<text top="749" left="57" width="455" height="13" font="3">but that it is logical that, in the clash with the guerrilla, regrettable fatalities would occur. </text>
<text top="761" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">4 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">15.The Salvadoran State also adds that applicable international law in an armed conflict is </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">International Humanitarian Law, specifically Article 3, which is common to the four Geneva </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="459" height="13" font="3">Conventions, supplemented by Protocol II. The State, in this regard, states the following:  </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="487" height="12" font="8">It is certain that, on principle, International Human Rights Law is applicable by governments, but in </text>
<text top="104" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">certain armed conflicts, as a result of the previously mentioned rules, International Humanitarian Law is </text>
<text top="115" left="57" width="390" height="12" font="8">binding on both sides, that is, for both the insurgents and government forces.….</text>
<text top="114" left="447" width="4" height="8" font="0"><a href="etree.html#4">2</a></text>
<text top="115" left="451" width="93" height="12" font="8"><a href="etree.html#4">  </a>[w]ith the above, </text>
<text top="126" left="57" width="488" height="12" font="8">although total enforcement [of International Humanitarian Law] probably  cannot be guaranteed in </text>
<text top="137" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">practice, there was an abundance of regulations, which even if only minimally enforced did provide an </text>
<text top="148" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">indication of protection of human rights for all Salvadorans; because this legal framework did exist, in </text>
<text top="158" left="57" width="487" height="12" font="8">addition to the surveillance and support that was given in this process of protection of human rights, </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="8">Professor Pastor Ridruejo concluded that the State did make available to the petitioners the guarantees </text>
<text top="180" left="57" width="266" height="12" font="8">and means to achieve an effective defense of their rights.”</text>
<text top="180" left="323" width="4" height="8" font="0"><a href="etree.html#4">3</a></text>
<text top="719" left="57" width="148" height="13" font="3">                                           </text>
<text top="730" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">2</text>
<text top="733" left="61" width="286" height="11" font="5"> Response from the State of March 5, 2005 to the initial petition, p. 2. </text>
<text top="743" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">3</text>
<text top="746" left="61" width="482" height="11" font="5">  In its response of March 5, the State cites the report submitted by professor José Antonio Pastor Ridruejo to the </text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="487" height="11" font="5">United Nations Commission on Human Rights, pursuant to the mandate granted by Resolution 1983/29 of that </text>
<text top="766" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">Commission, of January 19, 1984, in which the P.O.N. is determined to be in force [“Normal Operating Procedure for </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="456" height="11" font="5">detentions by the Armed Forces”]. That procedure establishes that minors found should be taken to safe places. </text>
<text top="179" left="327" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="191" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">16.On the basis of this information, the State requests the IACHR to rule that there was “[n]o </text>
<text top="216" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">systematic practice involving the disappearance of children by the Armed Forces of El </text>
<text top="228" left="57" width="56" height="13" font="3">Salvador.” </text>
<text top="240" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="252" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">17.Regarding the exhaustion of remedies under domestic law, the State contends that these </text>
<text top="264" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">remedies have not been exhausted. First, it notes that the petitioner filed a motion for the </text>
<text top="276" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">issuance of a writ of habeas corpus in 2002, that is, 22 years after the incident took place. The </text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Constitutional Law Chamber of the Supreme Court of Justice issued a ruling on March 3, 2003, </text>
<text top="301" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">dismissing the proceedings, contending that the petitioning party did not submit enough </text>
<text top="313" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">elements on the alleged missing child. The State claims that, on the basis of that judgment, </text>
<text top="325" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the Court departed from its previous case law rulings aimed at protecting the right to physical </text>
<text top="337" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">liberty of missing persons, because the parties did not provide sufficient background </text>
<text top="349" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">information. It further adds that, if the motion had been filed earlier, it would have been </text>
<text top="361" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">possible to gather more information. That State notes that this judiciary ruling does not </text>
<text top="374" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">exhaust domestic deliberations, because if the parties present fresh evidence concerning the </text>
<text top="386" left="57" width="430" height="13" font="3">alleged crime, a motion for the issuance of a new writ of habeas corpus can be filed. </text>
<text top="398" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="410" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">18. Regarding the criminal investigation, the Salvadoran State contends that the investigation </text>
<text top="422" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">phase continues in the Attorney General’s Office, and it is being conducted by the attorney </text>
<text top="434" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Daycel Marroquín. It indicates that, as part of the current investigation, on August 28, 2003, </text>
<text top="447" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">an investigator and the prosecutor in charge of the case, went to the place where the </text>
<text top="459" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">petitioner alleges that the incidents took place in order to gather information, but that it was </text>
<text top="471" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">not possible to gather any information because  many of the inhabitants from that time had </text>
<text top="483" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">died whereas others had left the area. It adds that, since the Supreme Court’s ruling on the </text>
<text top="495" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">issuance of a writ of habeas corpus, too little time has elapsed to finalize the investigation of </text>
<text top="507" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">the case, especially taking into consideration the time that has elapsed since the alleged </text>
<text top="519" left="57" width="80" height="13" font="3">disappearance. </text>
<text top="531" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="544" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">19. Furthermore, the State contends that the petitioners could have benefited from a series of </text>
<text top="556" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">alternate remedies such as the Government Commission on Human Rights of El Salvador. They </text>
<text top="568" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">could also have appealed to the International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC), which </text>
<text top="580" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">installed a permanent delegation in El Salvador during the conflict. The State adds that, on </text>
<text top="592" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">September 12, 1980, it signed a headquarters Agreement with the International Committee of </text>
<text top="604" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">the Red Cross to install a permanent delegation of this organization in El Salvador. By virtue of </text>
<text top="617" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">this agreement, the ICRC installed a search agency to record the requests made by relatives </text>
<text top="629" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">concerning persons who had supposedly been arrested or reported missing. Two of these </text>
<text top="641" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">offices were located in Santa Ana and San Miguel. It is argued that, in the document delivered </text>
<text top="653" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">by the ICRC on May 15, 1993 and compiling the reports received regarding disappearances </text>
<text top="665" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">from 1979 to 1992, there was no document reporting the disappearance of children. The State </text>
<text top="677" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">notes that the petitioners did not report the alleged incidents to any of these organizations. </text>
<text top="690" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">Because of this, the State requests the IACHR to declare the complaint inadmissible in </text>
<text top="702" left="57" width="430" height="13" font="3">accordance with the provisions of Article 31 of the Commission’s Rules of Procedure. </text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="9" size="10" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">5 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">20. Finally, the Salvadoran State contends that, because of the reservations made by the State </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">regarding its acceptance of the contentious jurisdiction of the Inter-American Court and </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">regarding what was established by the Court in its judgment about preliminary objections in </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">the case of the Serrano Cruz sisters, the case of the disappearance of José Adrián Rochac </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="319" height="13" font="3">Hernández could not come under the jurisdiction of said court. </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="20" height="13" font="1"><b>IV. </b></text>
<text top="141" left="92" width="172" height="13" font="1"><b>ANALYSIS OF ADMISSIBILITY </b></text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="15" height="13" font="1"><b>A. </b></text>
<text top="166" left="92" width="450" height="13" font="1"><b>Jurisdiction  <i>ratione</i></b><b>  <i>loci, ratione personae, ratione temporis</i></b><b>  and<i>ratione </i></b></text>
<text top="178" left="92" width="251" height="13" font="9"><i><b>materia</b></i><b>e of the Inter-American Commission </b></text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">21. Under the terms of Article 44 of the American Convention, the petitioners are in their </text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">lawful right to address a petition to the Commission. The petition that is being examined </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">indicates that the alleged victim was subject to the jurisdiction of the Salvadoran State at the </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">time of the alleged incidents. Regarding the State, the Commission notes that El Salvador is a </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">State Party to the American Convention, having duly deposited its instrument of ratification on </text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">June 23, 1978. As a consequence, the Commission has jurisdiction <i>ratione personae </i>to hear </text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="157" height="13" font="3">the complaints that were filed. </text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">22. Furthermore, the Commission has jurisdiction  <i>ratione materiae</i>  because the petitioners </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">claim violations of rights protected in the framework of the American Convention. The State </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">argues that International Humanitarian Law was the applicable law during the domestic armed </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">conflict. Regarding this, the Commission contends that it is not precluded from ruling on the </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">reported incidents merely because some of them might have occurred in the context of an </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">armed conflict. Article 27 of the Convention entitles the State to derogate certain obligations in </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the context of armed conflicts but in no way does it suspend the force of the Convention in its </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">entirety nor does it abridge the present Commission’s powers. The foregoing notwithstanding, </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">in the merits stage of the case, the IACHR must examine the State’s obligations stemming </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">from the Convention, in the light of the provisions of International Humanitarian Law, which </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="290" height="13" font="3">shall serve to interpret the case partially as <i>lex specialis.</i> </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="445" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">23.The Commission has jurisdiction <i>ratione temporis</i> to examine the complaints. The petition is </text>
<text top="457" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">based on allegations about incidents taking place as of August 25, 1982, which is the date </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">when José Adrián Rochac Hernández disappeared. The alleged incidents therefore took place </text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">after the entry into force of the obligations of the State as Party to the American Convention. </text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">In addition, as the petition alleges violations of rights protected in the framework of the </text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">American Convention in incidents taking place in the territory of a State Party, the Commission </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="330" height="13" font="3">concludes that it has jurisdiction <i>ratione loci</i> to hear the petition. </text>
<text top="530" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="15" height="13" font="1"><b>B. </b></text>
<text top="543" left="92" width="254" height="13" font="1"><b>Requirements for the petition’s admissibility </b></text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="14" height="13" font="1"><b>1. </b></text>
<text top="567" left="92" width="127" height="13" font="1"><b> of domestic remedies </b></text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">24.The State alleges that the present case is inadmissible because domestic remedies in El </text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">Salvador have not been exhausted. It notes that, in this regard, there are criminal proceedings </text>
<text top="615" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">in the investigative stage, and therefore the resolution of domestic remedies is still pending. </text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Likewise, it points out that available remedies were not exhausted on a timely basis, such as </text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the writ of habeas corpus, complaint filed with the International Committee of the Red Cross </text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">and the Government Commission on Human Rights. In this regard, the State points out that a </text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">motion for the issuance of a writ of habeas corpus was filed in 2002, although this motion </text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">could have been filed at any earlier time, and that this motion was dismissed for lack of </text>
<text top="688" left="57" width="237" height="13" font="3">presentation of evidence by the complainants. </text>
<text top="700" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">25.As for the petitioners, they claim that the domestic remedies are ineffectual, although </text>
<text top="725" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">despite this they have attempted all possible means, including a motion for the issuance of a </text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">writ of habeas corpus to determine the whereabouts of José Adrián Rochac Hernández. The </text>
<text top="749" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">petitioners emphasize that more than 25 years have elapsed since the disappearance of José </text>
<text top="761" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Adrián Rochac Hernández and that Salvadoran authorities have done nothing to guarantee the </text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">6 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">effectiveness of the investigation, find those responsible for the incidents, punish them, and </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">provide redress for the victims or their relatives. Regarding the criminal investigations, they </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">claim that, although it is true that the case is not closed, Salvadoran authorities have not </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">conducted an in-depth investigation to determine the whereabouts of the child. As claimed by </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the petitioners, the inactive role of the Attorney General’s Office shows that available domestic </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="190" height="13" font="3">remedies consist of mere formalities. </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">26.The present case alleges the presumed responsibility of the members of the Armed Forces </text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">of El Salvador in the forced disappearance of a child in the midst of a domestic armed conflict </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">in El Salvador. This period was characterized by systematic violations of human rights and </text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="423" height="13" font="3">impunity, facilitated in part by the ineffectiveness of El Salvador’s judiciary system.</text>
<text top="177" left="480" width="4" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#6">4</a></text>
<text top="457" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">28.Regarding the motion for the issuance of a writ of habeas corpus filed by the father of the </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">alleged victim, the IACHR concludes that, although it is the suitable remedy, it did not function </text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="482" height="13" font="3">adequately to determine the whereabouts of José Adrián Rochac Hernández. The Inter-</text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">American Court has ruled that the remedy of habeas corpus is essential to guarantee the life </text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">and integrity of arrested persons to prevent their disappearance or uncertainty about where </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="131" height="13" font="3">they are being detained.</text>
<text top="178" left="484" width="58" height="13" font="3"> In view of </text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">the particular circumstances of the  case and the above-mentioned context, the Commission </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">deems that, at the time the alleged incidents took place, it was not possible or necessary to </text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">file any motion, which serves as grounds for the exception to the rule of exhaustion of internal </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="357" height="13" font="3">remedies, as provided for by Article 46.2 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">27.The IACHR considers that, up to the date of the adoption of the present report, domestic </text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">remedies have not functioned effectively as required to investigate a report of forced </text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">disappearance. Indeed, almost 26 years have elapsed since the incidents took place, and since </text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">then the family of José Adrián Rochac Hernández has used various mechanisms that have </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">turned out to be ineffective to determine his whereabouts: the child’s father went to the only </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">existing institution to investigate cases of missing children, the nongovernmental organization </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="4"><i>Asociación Pro-Búsqueda</i>, in 1996. On May 31, 1996, the  <i>Asociación Pro-  Búsqueda</i>  filed a </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">complaint with the Office of the Public Prosecutor for the Defense of Human Rights of El </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">Salvador (Procuraduría para la Defensa de los Derechos Humanos de El Salvador—PDDH) </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">regarding 145 cases of children victims of forced disappearance, all of them in the context of </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the country’s domestic armed conflict. From these cases, the Office of the Prosecutors selected </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">five to conduct investigations; nevertheless, the case of José Adrián Rochac was not among </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">them. Likewise, on April 10, 2002, the father of the alleged victim filed a request for the </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">investigation of the whereabouts of  his son José Adrián Rochac, with the Soyapango </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Subregional Office of the Attorney General’s Office, as well as a motion for the issuance of a </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="223" height="13" font="3">writ of habeas corpus on October 17, 2002. </text>
<text top="445" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="517" left="188" width="4" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#6">5</a></text>
<text top="518" left="192" width="352" height="13" font="3"><a href="etree.html#6">  </a>In this regard, the IACHR observes that the remedy of habeas </text>
<text top="530" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">corpus has not functioned effectively in El Salvador in cases of forced disappearance, even </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">after the end of the conflict in 1992. The IACHR has received information provided by both </text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">parties that it is only recently, on March 20, 2002, by means of a judgment issued in the </text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">proceedings of Ana Julia and Carmelina Mejía Ramírez, that the Supreme Court changed its </text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">previous case law rulings when it accepted the violation of the right to physical liberty, even </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">when there was no evidence of detention. This case therefore represented the first possibility </text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">of effectively using of the remedy of habeas corpus in cases of disappeared persons in El </text>
<text top="615" left="57" width="48" height="13" font="3">Salvador.</text>
<text top="614" left="105" width="4" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#6">6</a></text>
<text top="649" left="57" width="148" height="13" font="3">                                           </text>
<text top="660" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">4</text>
<text top="663" left="61" width="482" height="11" font="5">  In its annual reports published during this conflict, the IACHR issued statements on several occasions about the </text>
<text top="673" left="57" width="339" height="11" font="5">violence and lack of due process of law for the enforcement of rights. For example: </text>
<text top="683" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">The right to justice has been profoundly affected by the state of emergency that reigns in El Salvador, as indicated </text>
<text top="693" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">earlier. Here it is worth reiterating the Commission’s remarks from its last Annual Report: the American Convention </text>
<text top="702" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">does not authorize the suspension of judicial guarantees that are essential for protecting basic rights, particularly not </text>
<text top="712" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">for prolonged periods, as has been the case in El Salvador. In addition, there is a lack of judicial independence and </text>
<text top="722" left="57" width="350" height="11" font="5">authority; members of the judiciary have themselves been the target of criminal acts. </text>
<text top="731" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">The marked limitations on judicial guarantees, as stated previously, have left many proceedings unresolved, causing </text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="225" height="11" font="5">the population to lose confidence in the judicial system </text>
<text top="750" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">5</text>
<text top="753" left="61" width="431" height="11" font="5"> I/A Court H.R., OC-8/87 of January 30, 1987, “Habeas Corpus with Suspension of Guarantees,” para. 44. </text>
<text top="762" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">6</text>
<text top="765" left="61" width="483" height="11" font="5">  Resolution of the Supreme Court of Justice of El Salvador, March 20, 2002, in the habeas corpus issuance </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="275" height="11" font="5">proceedings No. 379-2000, Ana Julia and Carmelina Mejía Ramírez. </text>
<text top="615" left="109" width="4" height="13" font="3"><a href="etree.html#6"> </a></text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="10" size="8" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="11" size="8" family="Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">7 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">29.After this modification in case law, the father of José Adrián filed a motion for the issuance </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">of a writ of habeas corpus in October 2002, which was dismissed by the courts. The ruling of </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the Constitutional Law Chamber of the Supreme Court on March 3, 2003, which dismissed the </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">motion, requires relatives to provide evidence to determine whether a forced disappearance </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">had occurred. The Commission observes that this State approach prevents the petitioners from </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">gaining access to this remedy, because the State passes on the obligation to investigate to the </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="79" height="13" font="3">alleged victims.</text>
<text top="128" left="136" width="4" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#7">7</a></text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">30.To deny access to jurisdiction by means of a writ of habeas corpus, the State claims that </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">the facts cannot be clarified because much time has elapsed since they occurred. In this </text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">regard, the IACHR considers that the writ of habeas corpus constitutes an efficient remedy to </text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">determine the whereabouts of a person although a long time has elapsed since that person’s </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="76" height="13" font="3">disappearance.</text>
<text top="129" left="140" width="4" height="13" font="3"><a href="etree.html#7"> </a></text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="201" left="133" width="4" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#7">8</a></text>
<text top="202" left="137" width="224" height="13" font="3"> In this specific case, Salvadoran legislation</text>
<text top="201" left="361" width="4" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#7">9</a></text>
<text top="202" left="365" width="177" height="13" font="3"> also provides that the “executing </text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">judge” in charge of enforcing the writ of habeas corpus has broad powers to request </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">information from state authorities and individuals, and Article 74 of this law on the </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">“responsibility of officials in the writ of habeas corpus” provides that there is “[n]o authority, </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">court or privileged jurisdiction in this matter.” According to the provisions of the judgment </text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">issued on this motion for a writ of habeas corpus, the steps taken by the executing judge were </text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="388" height="13" font="3">confined to observing whether there was a record of the child’s detention.</text>
<text top="274" left="445" width="8" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#7">10</a></text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="148" height="13" font="3">                                           </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">7</text>
<text top="622" left="61" width="481" height="11" font="5"> See, I/A Court H.R., <i>Bámaca Velásquez Case.</i> Judgment of November 25, 2000. Series C No. 70, para. 152, where </text>
<text top="632" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">the Court establishes that “[I]n cases of forced disappearance, the State's defense cannot rely on the impossibility of </text>
<text top="642" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">the plaintiff to  present evidence in the proceedings since, in such cases, it is the State that controls the means to </text>
<text top="651" left="57" width="487" height="11" font="5">clarify the facts that have occurred in its jurisdiction and, therefore, in practice, it is necessary to rely on the </text>
<text top="661" left="57" width="293" height="11" font="5">cooperation of the State itself in order to obtain the required evidence.” </text>
<text top="670" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">8</text>
<text top="673" left="61" width="481" height="11" font="5"> I/A Court H.R., <i>Case of the Serrano Cruz Sisters.</i><b> </b>Judgment of March 1, 2005. Series C No. 120, para. 79:“Among </text>
<text top="683" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">the indispensable judicial guarantees, habeas corpus represents the suitable means to guarantee liberty, monitor </text>
<text top="693" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">respect for the life and integrity of persons, and prevent their disappearance or the uncertainty of the whereabouts of </text>
<text top="702" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">their detention, to protect individuals against torture or other cruel treatments or penalties. In this regard, a writ of </text>
<text top="712" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">habeas  corpus may be an effective remedy to determine the whereabouts of a person or clarify whether there are </text>
<text top="722" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">grounds for qualifying a situation as undermining personal liberty, although the person for the benefit of whom the </text>
<text top="731" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">request if being filed is no longer in the custody of the State, but has been given to the custody of an individual or </text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="329" height="11" font="5">although a long period of time has elapsed since the disappearance of a person.” </text>
<text top="750" left="57" width="4" height="9" font="0">9</text>
<text top="753" left="61" width="281" height="11" font="5"> Articles 38 to 40 of the Constitutional Procedures Act of El Salvador. </text>
<text top="762" left="57" width="8" height="9" font="0">10</text>
<text top="765" left="65" width="478" height="11" font="5"> Judgment issued by the Constitutional Law Chamber of the Supreme Court of Justice of El Salvador, of March 3, </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="306" height="11" font="5">2003, in proceedings number 216-2002, of José Adrián Rochac Hernández. </text>
<text top="275" left="453" width="90" height="13" font="3">  On the basis of </text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">these characteristics and powers, the Commission considers that the Salvadoran State had the </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">mechanisms available to take steps aimed at locating the whereabouts of José Adrián Rochac </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">Hernández by a procedure of habeas corpus, despite the time that has elapsed since his </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="80" height="13" font="3">disappearance. </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">31.As a consequence, the IACHR concludes that the habeas corpus was the suitable remedy in </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">this case and that it was duly exhausted. The IACHR therefore considers that said requirement </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="392" height="13" font="3">as provided for in Article 46 of the Inter-American Convention has been met. </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">32.Despite the above, regarding the ongoing criminal investigation, the Commission concludes </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">that it does not have any information that would enable it to conclude that progress has been </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">made in determining the whereabouts of the child José Adrián Rochac. In this regard, the </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">information provided by both parties to the IACHR establishes that the two inquiries that were </text>
<text top="445" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">made during these proceedings involve requesting information from the<i>Asociación Pro- </i></text>
<text top="457" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="4"><i>Búsqueda</i>  on April 10, 2002, and the inquiry conducted on August 28, 2003, in which the </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">investigator and prosecutor in charge of the case went to the place where the petitioner claims </text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">the incident took place in order to gather information, which turned out to be fruitless. The </text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">IACHR considers that this does not constitute evidence that all the steps needed to locate the </text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">whereabouts of the child José Adrián Rochac have been taken, especially since the father of </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the alleged victim provided names of the persons allegedly responsible for the raid that led to </text>
<text top="530" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the death of the mother of the alleged victim, in addition to his disappearance, and there is no </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">evidence that they have ever been contacted. The IACHR concludes that the fact that there are </text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">current judicial proceedings, demonstrating that there is a legal activity aimed at making </text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">progress in the investigation during four years, provides grounds for the exception envisaged </text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="317" height="13" font="3">in the second part of Article 46.2 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">8 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">33.Therefore, subsidarily and regarding this criminal investigation, the Inter-American </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Commission decides to apply the exception envisaged in the second part of Article 46.2 of the </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">American Convention. As a result, the requirements envisaged in said international instrument </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">on the exhaustion of domestic remedies or the time-limits of six months for the submittal of </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="158" height="13" font="3">the petition are not applicable. </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">34.At the same time, the IACHR does not consider that a complaint lodged with the </text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">International Committee of the Red Cross is one of the remedies that must be exhausted </text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">according to the Convention. Said Committee is a humanitarian organization and does not </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="141" height="13" font="3">constitute a judiciary body. </text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">35.Finally, it should be pointed out that citing the exceptions to the rule on exhaustion of </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">domestic remedies set forth in the American Convention is closely tied to the finding of </text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">possible violations of certain rights enshrined in the Convention itself, such as effective judicial </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="491" height="13" font="3">protection. Article 46.2 of the American Convention, however, is a standard that is </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">independent of other substantive provisions of the same instrument. To determine whether the </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">exceptions to the exhaustion of domestic remedies also result in violations of the American </text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">Convention in the present case, a different review must be conducted in the merits stage of </text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">the case. This is because standards for assessing those exceptions are different from those </text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="453" height="13" font="3">used when assessing possible violations of Articles 8 and 25 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="14" height="13" font="1"><b>2. </b></text>
<text top="312" left="92" width="173" height="13" font="1"><b>Deadline for filing the petition </b></text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">36. According to Article 46.1.b of the Convention, the petition should be lodged within certain </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">time-limits to be  admitted, namely, within six months following the date on which the </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">complainant has been notified of the final judgment. In the present case, the Commission has </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">determined that the remedy of habeas corpus was duly exhausted. The ruling on this motion </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">was  notified on March 11, 2003. The petition was lodged on September 11, 2003, and </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="235" height="13" font="3">therefore it was lodged within the time-limits. </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="490" height="13" font="3">37.The Commission has subsidarily reviewed the situation stemming from the criminal </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">investigation currently under way, and has ruled that, regarding this, the exception provided </text>
<text top="445" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">for in the second part of Article 46.2 of the American Convention is applicable. Regarding this, </text>
<text top="457" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">Article 32 of the Rules of Procedure of the IACHR provides that, in cases where the exceptions </text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">to the requirement of exhaustion of domestic remedies are applicable, the petition must be </text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">lodged within a reasonable time, in the Commission’s opinion, taking into account the date of </text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="292" height="13" font="3">the alleged violation and the circumstances of each case. </text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">38.Regarding this, taking into account the date of the alleged incidents, the possibility of facing </text>
<text top="530" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">a situation of continued violation of human rights and the absence of elements that would </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">make it possible to determine whether an efficient criminal investigation has taken place, the </text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="489" height="13" font="3">Commission considers that, regarding the present criminal procedures, the petition being </text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="286" height="13" font="3">examined was lodged within a reasonable lapse of time. </text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="14" height="13" font="1"><b>3. </b></text>
<text top="591" left="92" width="248" height="13" font="1"><b>Duplication of proceedings and <i>res judicata</i></b><b> </b></text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="615" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">39.The exceptions provided for in Article 46.1.d and in Article 47.d of the American Convention </text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">have not been objected by the Salvadoran State nor do they stem from the information </text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="207" height="13" font="3">contained in the file of the present case. </text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="208" height="13" font="3">4. Characterization of the alleged events </text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="688" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">40.The petitioners allege that the incidents that were reported point to the violation of various </text>
<text top="700" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">rights enshrined in the American Convention on Human Rights (&#34;the American Convention&#34;): </text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">right to personal integrity  (Article 5); right to personal liberty (Article 7); right to a fair trial </text>
<text top="725" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">(Article 8); right to protection of the family (Article 17); right to a name (Article 18); rights of </text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">the child (Article 19); and right to judicial protection (Article 25), all in violation of the general </text>
<text top="749" left="57" width="256" height="13" font="3">duty to respect and guarantee rights (Article 1.1). </text>
<text top="761" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="788" left="296" width="6" height="9" font="0">9 </text>
<text top="800" left="57" width="2" height="9" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">41. By virtue of the principle <i>iura novit curia</i> and the repeated rulings based on case law issued </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">by the Commission and the Court to the effect that, if a forced disappearance is proven, it </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="239" height="13" font="3">would constitute a violation of the right to life,</text>
<text top="80" left="296" width="8" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#9">11</a></text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="488" height="13" font="3">42.Therefore, the IACHR considers that the alleged incidents, if proven, would constitute </text>
<text top="129" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">violations of the rights protected by Articles 4, 5, 7, 8, 17, 18, 19, and 25, all in connection </text>
<text top="141" left="57" width="213" height="13" font="3">with Article 1 of the American Convention.</text>
<text top="81" left="304" width="238" height="13" font="3"> the IACHR is also admitting the present case </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="264" height="13" font="3">on the grounds of a presumed violation of Article 4. </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="140" left="271" width="8" height="9" font="0"><a href="etree.html#9">12</a></text>
<text top="710" left="57" width="148" height="13" font="3">                                           </text>
<text top="721" left="57" width="8" height="9" font="0">11</text>
<text top="724" left="65" width="476" height="11" font="5"> See, for example, the I/A Court H.R., <i>Castillo Páez Case</i>. Judgment of November 3, 1998. Series C No. 34, para. 66. </text>
<text top="733" left="57" width="8" height="9" font="0">12</text>
<text top="736" left="65" width="477" height="11" font="5"> The Commission puts on record that, although an account has been given of the grave incidents that were reported </text>
<text top="746" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">regarding the alleged execution of Mrs. Silverio, mother of José Adrián Rochac Hernández, and his brother, Sergio </text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="486" height="11" font="5">Antonio Rochac Hernández, they have not been the object of any specific complaint, nor has any information been </text>
<text top="766" left="57" width="485" height="11" font="5">given about any proceedings being filed to exhaust domestic remedies about it. The Commission therefore shall not be </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="355" height="11" font="5">reviewing the alleged responsibility of the State for these incidents in the present case. </text>
<text top="141" left="279" width="4" height="13" font="3"><a href="etree.html#9"> </a></text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="15" height="13" font="1"><b>V. </b></text>
<text top="166" left="92" width="86" height="13" font="1"><b>CONCLUSIONS </b></text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">43. The Inter-American Commission concludes that it is competent to hear this case and that </text>
<text top="202" left="57" width="469" height="13" font="3">the petition is admissible in accordance with Articles 46 and 47 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="214" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="226" left="57" width="487" height="13" font="3">44. On the basis of the factual and legal arguments indicated above and without prejudging </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="118" height="13" font="3">the merits of the case, </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="263" left="136" width="327" height="13" font="1"><b>THE INTER-AMERICAN COMMISSION ON HUMAN RIGHTS, </b></text>
<text top="275" left="270" width="58" height="13" font="1"><b>DECIDES: </b></text>
<text top="287" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="299" left="57" width="486" height="13" font="3">1.To declare that the present case is admissible in regard to the alleged violations of the rights </text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="427" height="13" font="3">protected by Articles 1.1, 4, 5, 7, 8, 17, 18, 19 and 25 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="201" height="13" font="3">2. To notify the parties of this decision, </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="267" height="13" font="3">3.To continue examining the merits of the case, and </text>
<text top="372" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="384" left="57" width="465" height="13" font="3">4. To publish this decision and include it in its Annual Report to the OAS General Assembly. </text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="4" height="13" font="3"> </text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="295" height="13" font="3">Done and signed in the city of Washington, D.C., on the 21</text>
<text top="408" left="352" width="6" height="9" font="0">st</text>
<text top="409" left="358" width="185" height="13" font="3"> day of the month of October, 2006. </text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="485" height="13" font="3">(Signed): Evelio Fernández Arévalos,  President; Paulo Sérgio Pinheiro, FirstVice-President; </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="397" height="13" font="3">Freddy Gutiérrez, Paolo G. Carozza and Víctor E. Abramovich, Commissioners. </text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
