<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="23.08.0">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="842" width="595">
	<fontspec id="0" size="10" family="BAAAAA+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="10" family="CAAAAA+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="6" family="CAAAAA+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="8" family="DAAAAA+TimesNewRomanPSMT" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="8" family="CAAAAA+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="57" left="247" width="102" height="12" font="0"><b>REPORT Nº 26/00</b></text>
<text top="69" left="265" width="66" height="12" font="1">CASE 11.821</text>
<text top="81" left="240" width="115" height="12" font="1">VILLAGE OF MOIWANA</text>
<text top="93" left="271" width="54" height="12" font="1">SURINAME</text>
<text top="105" left="261" width="73" height="12" font="1">March 7, 2000</text>
<text top="130" left="57" width="9" height="12" font="0"><b>I.</b></text>
<text top="130" left="92" width="57" height="12" font="0"><b>SUMMARY</b></text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">1. The petition was lodged by the human rights organization Moiwana ’86 of Suriname on June</text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">27, 1997, and concerns the extrajudicial execution of more than 40 residents of Moiwana, a</text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">village belonging to one of Suriname’s maroon communities, and the intentional destruction of</text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">their property by members of the Army of that country. The petition also addresses the failure</text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">to provide a fair trial with due process, and compensation for those acts. The State did not</text>
<text top="215" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">answered the Commission’s requests for information about the petition. The Commission after</text>
<text top="227" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">analyzing the petition and the fulfillment of the requisites provided for the application of the</text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">American Declaration on the Rights and Duties of Man (the “Declaration”) and the American</text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Convention on Human Rights (the “Convention”), decided to declare the case admissible in</text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">respect to alleged violations of Articles I, right to life, liberty and personal security; VII. right</text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">to protection for mothers and children; IX. right to inviolability of the home; XXIII, right to</text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">property; all of them of the Declaration; and Articles 8(1), right to a fair trial; and 25(2) right</text>
<text top="300" left="57" width="430" height="12" font="1">to judicial protection, and Article 1(1) Obligation to respect rights of the Convention. </text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="15" height="12" font="0"><b>II.</b></text>
<text top="324" left="107" width="201" height="12" font="0"><b>PROCESSING BY THE COMMISSION </b></text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">2.   The   Commission   received   the   petition   on   June   27,   1997,   and   transmitted   it   to   the</text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Government on October 30 of that year, requesting a reply within the next 90 days. Faced with</text>
<text top="373" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the Government’s failure to reply, the Commission repeated the request on two occasions,</text>
<text top="385" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">June 2, 1998, and February 25, 1999, indicating that it would consider application of Article 42</text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">of its Regulations in the event no reply were received within the next 30 days. To date the</text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="302" height="12" font="1">Commission has not received any response from the State. </text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="177" height="12" font="0"><b>III. POSITION OF THE PARTIES</b></text>
<text top="458" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="0"><b>A.</b></text>
<text top="458" left="107" width="83" height="12" font="0"><b>The petitioner </b></text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">3. By way of general background information, the petition says that in 1980 a group of officers</text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">of the National Army of Suriname carried out a  coup d’état  and their leader, Desi Bouterse,</text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">declared   himself   Commander-in-Chief   of   the   Army.   Those   military   officers   proceeded   to</text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">appoint a civilian administration, which announced it would call elections. However, no such</text>
<text top="531" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">elections were ever held and instead there followed a period of serious and systematic human</text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="409" height="12" font="1">rights violations, which were documented overall by the IACHR in several report<a href="etree.html#1">s</a></text>
<text top="543" left="466" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#1">1</a></text>
<text top="543" left="470" width="4" height="12" font="1"><a href="etree.html#1">.</a></text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">4. As specific background information, the petition mentions that in 1986 an armed opposition</text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">group (the  “Jungle  Commando”)  was set up with the  support  of Surnames exiles living  in</text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Holland and under the leadership of Ronnie Brunswick, a former member of Desi Bouterse’s</text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">guard. That group’s initial activities were attacks on military posts in Eastern Suriname in the</text>
<text top="616" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">territory   of   the   Ndjuka   maroons,   the   people   to   which   Brunswick   and   most   of   his   armed</text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">followers   belong.   The   Army   responded   with   extensive   operations   in   the   region   and   with</text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">systematic and collective reprisals against the civilian maroon population, alleging they were</text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">collaborating with the Jungle Commando. Villages of maroons who belonged to other tribes</text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">and lived in different regions were targeted for reprisal by the Surnames Army, which killed</text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="478" height="12" font="1">between 150 and 200 civilians. It should be recalled, inter alia, that the IACHR documente<a href="etree.html#1">d</a></text>
<text top="676" left="535" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#1">2</a></text>
<text top="689" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">cases where the maroons had been made victims of forced starvation, illegal cuts in benefits,</text>
<text top="701" left="57" width="84" height="12" font="1">and “ethnocide.”</text>
<text top="701" left="141" width="2" height="7" font="2"> </text>
<text top="742" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">1</text>
<text top="744" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="743" left="65" width="473" height="10" font="4">Reports   on   the   Situation   of   Human   Rights   in   Suriname,   1983   and   1985,   several   resolutions   (including   those</text>
<text top="754" left="57" width="481" height="10" font="4">published in the 1988-89 Annual Report, p. 123-54) and two cases before the Inter-American Court (Nº 10.150 and</text>
<text top="763" left="57" width="35" height="10" font="4">10.274).</text>
<text top="773" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">2</text>
<text top="776" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="775" left="63" width="171" height="10" font="4">IACHR 1986-97 Annual Report, p. 263-65.</text>
<text top="802" left="296" width="4" height="7" font="2">1</text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="842" width="595">
<text top="57" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">5. The petition states with respect to the massacre and destruction at the village of Moiwana,</text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">which is the principal subject of the petition, that at the beginning of November 1986 the</text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">military   commenced  a  “cleansing”   operation   in   Eastern   Suriname,   and   ordered   the   civilian</text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">population   to   evacuate   the   area.   For   various   reasons   many   did   not   leave.   The   operation</text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">against   the  village   of Moiwana and  its outlying  areas began,  according  to  the  petition,   on</text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">November 29, 1986, and was carried out by a military unit made up of specially-trained men</text>
<text top="130" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">divided into three groups, one of which launched a direct attack on the village. This action</text>
<text top="142" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">started with the burning of the house belonging to the rebel leader, Brunswick, and continued</text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">with the shooting of nearly all the inhabitants, after which the village was burned. At the same</text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">time the soldiers blew up a bus that was approaching, killing all the occupants. After these</text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">events   were   over   40   people   were   dead,   victims   of   extrajudicial   execution   by   government</text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">troops. Some of the corpses that were taken to the morgue in Alfonsdorp were incinerated</text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">next  to   the   morgue  building.  Toward  the   end  of November   1986,  the  Government  denied</text>
<text top="215" left="57" width="235" height="12" font="1">having carried out any operations in the area. </text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">6. According to the petition, in 1989 the Civil Police attempted to carry out an investigation led</text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">by Police Inspector Herman E. Gooding, who was murdered on August 4, 1990, after meeting</text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="474" height="12" font="1">with the Deputy Commander of the Military Police, as documented in the report by the IACHR</text>
<text top="263" left="531" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#2">3</a></text>
<text top="263" left="535" width="4" height="12" font="1"><a href="etree.html#2">.</a></text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">His corpse was found next to the office of Commander-in-Chief Bouterse. Several soldiers were</text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">arrested by the Civil Police shortly after the Moiwana massacre, but were released after the</text>
<text top="300" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">police were besieged by 30 armed Military Policemen acting on the orders of Commander-in-</text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="81" height="12" font="1">Chief Bouterse. </text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">7. In 1992, the Parliament of Suriname adopted a retroactive Amnesty Law that canceled all</text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">proceedings   related   to   human   rights   violations   committed   from   1985   to   1991,   except   for</text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">crimes against humanity defined by the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the</text>
<text top="373" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Crime of Genocide (1948) and the Charter of the Nuremberg Tribunal of 1950 (Nuremberg</text>
<text top="385" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Principles). According to the petitioners, the foregoing means that the aforesaid Amnesty Law</text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="208" height="12" font="1">does not apply to the crimes of Moiwana.</text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">8. On the question of the law, the petition alleges violation by the Government of Suriname of</text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">Articles I, right to life and personal security; VII, right to protection for mothers and children; IX,</text>
<text top="446" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">right to inviolability of the home; and XXIII, right to property of the American Declaration of the</text>
<text top="458" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Rights and Duties of Man (hereinafter the “American Declaration”); Articles 8 (1), right to a fair</text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">trial; and 25(1) and 25(2), right to judicial protection of the American Convention on Human</text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Rights. The petition further alleges violation of Article 3 of the Geneva Convention of August</text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">12,   1949;   and   Articles   4   and   13   of   the   Protocol   Additional   to   the   forenamed   convention,</text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Relating to the Protection of Victims of Non-International Armed Conflicts (Protocol II), 1978,</text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">and of international criminal law related to the prohibition and punishment of crimes against</text>
<text top="531" left="57" width="54" height="12" font="1">humanity. </text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">9. The  petitioner  pleads  exception   to  the  requirement of exhaustion  of domestic  remedies</text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">based on the grounds contained in Article 37(2)(b) and (c) of the Regulations of the IACHR,</text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">which refer, respectively, to denial of access to the remedies under domestic law or prevention</text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="395" height="12" font="1">from exhausting them, and to unwarranted delay in rendering a final judgment. </text>
<text top="616" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">10. The petitioners claim that the Attorney General and the President of the Court are the only</text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">ones   who   could   have   ordered   an   investigation   and   filed   criminal   charges   against   those</text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">responsible, but that neither of them had opened a meaningful investigation into the Moiwana</text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">massacre,   nor   adopted   any   measures   either   to   implement   the   recommendations   that   the</text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Commission made in five decisions that it published in its 1989 Annual Report, or against the</text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">mass repression inflicted by the Army in 1986 in the village of Moiwana and other locations</text>
<text top="689" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">against Maroons and Amerindians, which led to their exile en masse in French Guyana and</text>
<text top="701" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Paramaribo. The petitioner alleges that the State has provided no compensation at all to any of</text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the victims, be they the residents of the village of Moiwana or the refugees, 10,000 of whom</text>
<text top="725" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">were still living in refugee camps near St. Laurent, in French Guyana at the time the petition</text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="64" height="12" font="1">was lodged. </text>
<text top="773" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">3</text>
<text top="776" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="775" left="63" width="171" height="10" font="4">IACHR 1990-91 Annual Report, p. 497-98.</text>
<text top="802" left="296" width="4" height="7" font="2">2</text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="842" width="595">
<text top="57" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">11. The petitioners further assert that there was unwarranted delay of justice in accordance</text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">with Article 37(c) of the Regulations of the IACHR, given that the massacre took place on</text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">November 29, 1986, more than 10 years before the petition was filed and yet the court had</text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">still not issued a final decision. The petitioners claim that prior to 1992, one could understand</text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">why the civil, elected, and judicial authorities should have failed to investigate and administer</text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">justice because the Armed Force were in control and democracy was weak. They contend that</text>
<text top="130" left="57" width="260" height="12" font="1">after that date such reasoning was no longer valid. </text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">12. The petitioners report that in May 1993 a mass grave was found containing a number of</text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">corpses of the victims from the village of Moiwana, and that the Ministry of Justice and the</text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">police indicated that the legal investigation and prosecution of the matter were not priorities</text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">for that administration, and that the country’s economic and social problems took precedence.</text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">For its part, the Ministry of Social Affairs and Housing, declared in a press conference at the</text>
<text top="215" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">time that the Moiwana massacre must be deemed covered by the Amnesty Law that had been</text>
<text top="227" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">passed, and, therefore, was not justiciable. By the same token, the petitioners report that</text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">despite   identification   of   several   of   the   corpses   (of   five   to   seven   adults   and   two   to   three</text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">children) in the grave as members of the Moiwana community, no measures whatever were</text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="48" height="12" font="1">adopted. </text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">13. The petitioners also say that the Parliament of Suriname adopted in December 1995 a</text>
<text top="300" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">motion   requiring   the   Executive   Branch   immediately   to   open   an   investigation   into   several</text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">infamous violations committed during the military regime, including the Moiwana massacre,</text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">but that no action was taken either. The petitioners also mention that they have repeatedly</text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">requested the authorities to adopt measures on the matter, to no avail. The petitioners state</text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">that   under  Surnames  law, at  the   request  of  a private  claimant  the  Supreme  Court,  if  the</text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">request is justified, is required to ask the Attorney General to undertake an investigation into</text>
<text top="373" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the matter in question. Accordingly, the petitioners made such a request and the President of</text>
<text top="385" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the Supreme Court informed them that he had solicited information from the Attorney General</text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">but that the latter had not provided it to him. The petition claims that the party that won the</text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">elections   and   establishes   judicial   priorities   is   under   the   leadership   of   Desire   Bouterse,   the</text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">military  officer  who  headed the  military  regime  that  carried out  the  alleged  violations,  for</text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="396" height="12" font="1">which reason it is unlikely that the Government will adopt a different attitude. </text>
<text top="458" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">14. The petitioners attach official documents, together with reports on the situation supporting</text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">the   foregoing   allegations   published   internationally   by   governments   and   non-governmental</text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">organizations.  For all these reasons they request that the  exception to the requirement to</text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="209" height="12" font="1">exhaust domestic remedies be accepted. </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="0"><b>B.</b></text>
<text top="518" left="92" width="54" height="12" font="0"><b>The State</b></text>
<text top="518" left="146" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">15. Notwithstanding repeated requests by the Commission made on October 30, 1997, June</text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">2,1998, and February 25, 1999, the latter indicating that the Commission will consider the</text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">application of Article 42 of its Regulations if no answer were received within 30 days, the State</text>
<text top="579" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">of Suriname did not reply to any of those requests for comments. The Commission considers</text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="416" height="12" font="1">consequently that the State has not controverted the facts alleged in the petition. </text>
<text top="616" left="57" width="17" height="12" font="0"><b>IV.</b></text>
<text top="616" left="93" width="169" height="12" font="0"><b>ANALYSIS OF ADMISSIBILITY</b></text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="0"><b>A.</b></text>
<text top="640" left="129" width="410" height="12" font="0"><b>Competence  ratione   personae,   ratione   materiae,   ratione   tempori   and</b></text>
<text top="652" left="129" width="171" height="12" font="0"><b>ratione loci of the Commission</b></text>
<text top="652" left="300" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">16. The petitioners claim that the State of Suriname violated rights of the inhabitants of the</text>
<text top="689" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">village of Moiwana recognized in Articles I, VII, IX, and XXIII of the Declaration; and in Articles</text>
<text top="701" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">8(1), and 25(1) and 25(2) of the Convention, by facts occurred in the Surnames territory</text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="283" height="12" font="1">affecting natural persons under Suriname’s jurisdiction. </text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">17. The Commission considers it is competent ratione materiae, ratione personae and ratione</text>
<text top="749" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">loci in this case to analyze the complaint in reference to presumed violations to the Declaration</text>
<text top="761" left="57" width="106" height="12" font="1">and the Convention. </text>
<text top="802" left="296" width="4" height="7" font="2">3</text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="842" width="595">
	<fontspec id="5" size="5" family="CAAAAA+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="57" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">18.  Suriname,  as  a  member  state   of  the   OAS  is  bound   both  to   the   Declaration  since  the</text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">beginning to its membership to the OAS on June 8, 1977; and to the Convention which it has</text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">ratified on November 12¸1987. The original events that originated the petition, specifically the</text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">alleged attack on the village of Moiwana and the extrajudicial executions and other violations</text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">denounced, would have happened on November 29, 1986, while the Declaration was in force in</text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">regard to Suriname. In reference to the Convention, the facts referring to its duty in respect to</text>
<text top="130" left="57" width="319" height="12" font="1">legal guarantees and due process are of a continuous nature<a href="etree.html#4">.</a></text>
<text top="130" left="376" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#4">4</a></text>
<text top="130" left="380" width="159" height="12" font="1"><a href="etree.html#4">.</a> Therefore, the Commission is</text>
<text top="142" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">competence  ratione tempore  with regard to those facts as per the competent given by the</text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="60" height="12" font="1">Convention.</text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">19. In those matters specifically referred to the Declaration, the Commission is competent to</text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">know the case because the allegations referred to violations of rights recognized in its Article I</text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">(right to life, liberty and personal security); VII (right to protection for mothers and children);</text>
<text top="215" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">IX (right to inviolability of the home); and XXIII (right to property) as indicated by Articles 26</text>
<text top="227" left="57" width="129" height="12" font="1">and 51 of its Regulation<a href="etree.html#4">s.</a></text>
<text top="227" left="186" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#4">5</a></text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">20. The Commission is also competent with respect to the Convention, to examine the alleged</text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">facts that may constitute violation or continuous denegation of justice as per Articles 8 and 25</text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">(right to judicial guarantees, and rights to due legal process) in relation with Article 1(1). By</text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">its   ratification   of   the   Convention,   Suriname   assumed   the   duty   to   respect   all   rights   and</text>
<text top="300" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">freedoms recognized in the Convention and to guarantee its full and free enjoyment to all</text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="150" height="12" font="1">persons under its jurisdictio<a href="etree.html#4">n</a></text>
<text top="312" left="208" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#4">6</a></text>
<text top="312" left="211" width="327" height="12" font="1"><a href="etree.html#4">  </a>(Article 1(1)), including judicial guarantees and protection, as</text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">stated   in   Articles   8   and   25.   According   to   the   Inter-American   Court   on   Human   Rights   this</text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">obligation implies the duty of the State party to organize the governmental apparatus and, in</text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">general, all the structures through which public power is exercised, so that they are capable of</text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="318" height="12" font="1">juridical ensuring the free and full enjoyment of human rights. </text>
<text top="385" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">21. Consequently, the Commission has competence  ratione tempore  to examine and decide</text>
<text top="397" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the instant case, in relation to the violations allegedly occurred before Suriname’s ratification</text>
<text top="409" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">of the Convention, as well as in relation with the Convention in reference to proceedings and</text>
<text top="421" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">activities or inactions by the State of Suriname as continuing violations of Articles 8 and 25 of</text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="242" height="12" font="1">the Convention, in relation with its Article 1(1). </text>
<text top="458" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">22. The Commission considers as well necessary to examine the admissibility in relation with</text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the positive obligation indicated in Article 1(1) of the Convention (obligation to respect the</text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">rights and freedoms recognized and to guarantee its full and free exercise). In that sense the</text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="261" height="12" font="1">Commission reminds what the Court has indicated: </text>
<text top="518" left="92" width="410" height="12" font="1">Basically, the measures the Court may impose constitute the protection of the</text>
<text top="531" left="92" width="410" height="12" font="1">law   for   the   rights   provided   by   the   Convention   which   in   light   of   the   positive</text>
<text top="543" left="92" width="410" height="12" font="1">obligation contained in Article 1(1) obligating states to respect and guarantee</text>
<text top="555" left="92" width="410" height="12" font="1">them,   implies,   as   the   Court   has   stated…   the   duty   of   the   States   Parties   to</text>
<text top="567" left="92" width="410" height="12" font="1">organize the governmental apparatus and, in general, all the structures through</text>
<text top="579" left="92" width="410" height="12" font="1">which public power is exercised, so that they are capable of juridically ensuring</text>
<text top="591" left="92" width="225" height="12" font="1">the free and full enjoyment of human right<a href="etree.html#4">s.</a></text>
<text top="591" left="317" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#4">7</a></text>
<text top="616" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">23.   While   petitioners   do   not   explicitly   invoke   violation   of   Article   1(1),   either   as   positive</text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">obligation, and in relation to other Articles recognized in the Convention that allegedly have</text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">been   violated,   the   Commission   in   consideration   of   the   facts   denounced   considers   it   shall</text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">examine the eventual violation of Article 1 to establish if the State of Suriname has violated in</text>
<text top="678" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">4</text>
<text top="681" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="680" left="63" width="264" height="10" font="4">Cf. CIDH Case 11.516 Ovelario Tames. Report Nº 60/99, April 13</text>
<text top="680" left="328" width="5" height="6" font="5">th</text>
<text top="680" left="332" width="206" height="10" font="4">, 1999. Paras. 26 and 27. Annual Report 1998, Vol</text>
<text top="690" left="57" width="35" height="10" font="4">I, p.446.</text>
<text top="700" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">5</text>
<text top="703" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="702" left="63" width="474" height="10" font="4">The fact that Suriname had ratified the American Convention on November 12, 1987, does not exempt it from the</text>
<text top="712" left="57" width="481" height="10" font="4">responsibility for acts that violate human rights and that had ocurred before its ratification, but are guaranteed by the</text>
<text top="722" left="57" width="481" height="10" font="4">American Declaration, which has binding force, as per Advisory Opinion Nº 10, Inter-American Court of Human Rights.</text>
<text top="732" left="57" width="481" height="10" font="4">Interpretation of the American Declaration on the Rights and Duties of Man within the framework of Article 64 of the</text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="320" height="10" font="4">American Convention on Human Rights. Serie A. Decisions and Opinions.Nº 10.</text>
<text top="751" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">6</text>
<text top="754" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="753" left="63" width="363" height="10" font="4">I.A. Court HR. Godinez Cruz Case, Judgment of January 20, 1989, Serie C. Nº 5 par. 175.</text>
<text top="763" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">7</text>
<text top="766" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="765" left="63" width="475" height="10" font="4">I.A. Court HR. Velásquez Rodríguez Case, Judgment of July 29, 1988, Serie C. Nº 4. par. 164. Godinez Cruz Case,</text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="222" height="10" font="4">Judgment of January 20, 1989, Serie C .Nº 5 par. 175.</text>
<text top="802" left="296" width="4" height="7" font="2">4</text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="842" width="595">
<text top="57" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the instant case its obligation to respect and guarantee the rights to judicial guarantees and</text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="58" height="12" font="1">protection. </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="0"><b>B.</b></text>
<text top="93" left="122" width="310" height="12" font="0"><b>Other requirements for the admissibility of the petition</b></text>
<text top="93" left="432" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="10" height="12" font="0"><b>a.</b></text>
<text top="117" left="92" width="186" height="12" font="0"><b>Exhaustion of domestic remedies</b></text>
<text top="117" left="279" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="142" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">24. Article 46 of the Convention stipulates that for a case to be admitted will be required, “that</text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the   remedies   under   domestic   law   have   been   pursued   and   exhausted   in   accordance   with</text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">generally recognized  principles  of international  law.” However, the  Convention  provides for</text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">exceptions to this requirement when the domestic law does not provide  de facto  or  de jure</text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">remedies.   Indeed,   Article   46(2)   specifies   that   the   above   is   the   case   when   the   domestic</text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">legislation of the state concerned does not afford due process of law for the protection of the</text>
<text top="215" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">right or rights that have allegedly been violated; the party alleging violation of his rights has</text>
<text top="227" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">been   denied   access   to   the   remedies   under   domestic   law   or   has   been   prevented   from</text>
<text top="239" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">exhausting them; or there has been unwarranted delay in rendering a final judgment under</text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the aforementioned remedies. In the instant case, it emerges from what is documented by the</text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">petitioner, and not challenged by the State, that, in practice, the petitioner was denied access</text>
<text top="275" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">to those remedies; that the authorities in charge of pressing forward proceedings failed even</text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">to   institute   them,   much   less   complete   them;   that   the   initial   investigations,   the   basis   for</text>
<text top="300" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">possible remedies, were obstructed by agents of the State; and that an Amnesty Law was</text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">interpreted   by   the   authorities   as   relieving   them   of   the   obligation   to   prosecute   those</text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="64" height="12" font="1">responsible. </text>
<text top="348" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">25. As indicated by the Court, the exception to the rule of exhaustion of domestic remedies</text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="265" height="12" font="1">results, following the principles of international law: </text>
<text top="385" left="93" width="409" height="12" font="1">… in the first place that this is a rule that may be waived, either expressly or by</text>
<text top="397" left="93" width="409" height="12" font="1">implication, by the State having the right to invoke it as this Court has already</text>
<text top="409" left="93" width="410" height="12" font="1">recognized ( see Viviana Gallardo et al. Judgment of November 13,1981, Nº G</text>
<text top="421" left="93" width="409" height="12" font="1">101/81, Series A, para. 26). Second, the objection asserting the non-exhaustion</text>
<text top="433" left="93" width="409" height="12" font="1">of domestic  remedies,  to   be  timely,   must  be  made  at  an early stage  of the</text>
<text top="446" left="93" width="410" height="12" font="1">proceedings by the State entitled to make it, lest a waiver of the requirement be</text>
<text top="458" left="93" width="53" height="12" font="1">presumed<a href="etree.html#5">.</a></text>
<text top="458" left="146" width="4" height="7" font="2"><a href="etree.html#5">8</a></text>
<text top="482" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">26.   Petitioners   invoked   in   their   original   complaint   the   exception   to   the   requirement   of</text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">exhaustion   of  domestic   remedies,   based  on the  inexistence   of an  effective   remedy  and   in</text>
<text top="506" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">unjustified   delay   in   the   proceedings.   Consequently,   the   burden   of   the   proof   to   deny   this</text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">statement   by   the   petitioners   becomes   a   responsibility   of   the   State.   By   not   answering   the</text>
<text top="531" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">repeated   requests   for   comments   to   the   complaint,   the   State   has   not   controverted   these</text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">allegations and renounced its right to oppose this exception. The Commission concludes that</text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the requirement in relation with the exhaustion of domestic remedies has been satisfied in the</text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="68" height="12" font="1">instant case. </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="0"><b>b.</b></text>
<text top="591" left="92" width="214" height="12" font="0"><b>Period for presentation of the petition</b></text>
<text top="591" left="306" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="616" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">27. In the original  complaint  petitioner  explained  the reasons to consider  the  presentation</text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">done within a reasonable period. Petitioner alleged that the case was presented ten years after</text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the originating facts, an that during the first four years of that period the Government was</text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">ruled or  de facto  controlled by a military regime, reason that impeded the initiation of the</text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">domestic remedies. Moreover, the amnesty established by Parliament in 1987 had voided the</text>
<text top="676" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">possibility   for   the   victims   to   obtain   due   judicial   reparation.   After   1991,   already   under   a</text>
<text top="689" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">constitutionally   elected   government,   government   representatives   declared   in   several</text>
<text top="701" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">opportunities their lack of interest in pursuing their obligation to investigate and to prosecute</text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">those responsible, and to make reparations to the victims. Petitioner alleged that during all</text>
<text top="725" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">that period, representatives of the victims made repeated attempts to spur the authorities into</text>
<text top="737" left="57" width="94" height="12" font="1">action to no avail. </text>
<text top="773" left="57" width="4" height="7" font="2">8</text>
<text top="776" left="61" width="2" height="9" font="3"> </text>
<text top="775" left="63" width="446" height="10" font="4">I.A. Court HR. Caso Godinez Cruz, Preliminary Objections (Judgment of June 26,1987) Series C.Nº 3 para. 90.</text>
<text top="802" left="296" width="4" height="7" font="2">5</text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="842" width="595">
<text top="57" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">28.   It   is   incumbent   upon   the   State   the   burden   of   proof   to   deny   those   allegations.   The</text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Commission considers that in the instant case the conditions have been fulfilled in relation to</text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">the presentation within a reasonable period as stated by Article 46(2) of the Convention, and</text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="205" height="12" font="1">Articles 38(2) and 52 of its Regulations. </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="10" height="12" font="0"><b>c.</b></text>
<text top="117" left="92" width="150" height="12" font="0"><b>Duplication of proceedings</b></text>
<text top="117" left="242" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="142" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">29. According to the record, the petition is not pending in another international proceeding for</text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">settlement as prescribed by Article 46(1)(c) of the American Convention, nor is it substantially</text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">the same as one previously studied by the Commission or by another international organization in</text>
<text top="178" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">accordance with Article 47(d) of the Convention. The State has not challenged the petition on</text>
<text top="190" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">grounds   of   duplication   of   proceedings.   Accordingly,   the   Commission   finds   that   there   is   no</text>
<text top="203" left="57" width="235" height="12" font="1">duplication of proceedings in the instant case. </text>
<text top="227" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="0"><b>d.</b></text>
<text top="227" left="92" width="291" height="12" font="0"><b>Characterization of the facts to establish a violation</b></text>
<text top="227" left="383" width="4" height="12" font="1"> </text>
<text top="251" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">30. The alleged facts if proven, may characterize violations of Articles I, VII, IX, and XXIII of</text>
<text top="263" left="57" width="304" height="12" font="1">the Declaration and Articles 8, 25, and 1 of the Convention. </text>
<text top="288" left="57" width="108" height="12" font="0"><b>V. CONCLUSIONS </b></text>
<text top="312" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">31. The   Commission  concludes   that  it  is  competent  to   examine  the   instant   case,  that  the</text>
<text top="324" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">petition is admissible, in conformity with Articles 52 and 38(2) of its Regulations in what refers</text>
<text top="336" left="57" width="408" height="12" font="1">to the Declaration and with same Article 38(2) in what refers to the Convention. </text>
<text top="360" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">32. On the basis of the arguments of fact and law analyzed, and without prejudging the merits</text>
<text top="373" left="57" width="74" height="12" font="1">of the matter, </text>
<text top="397" left="136" width="323" height="12" font="0"><b>THE INTER-AMERICAN COMMISSION ON HUMAN RIGHTS,</b></text>
<text top="409" left="271" width="54" height="12" font="0"><b>DECIDES:</b></text>
<text top="433" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">1. To declare the instant case admissible in relation to alleged violations to Articles I, right to</text>
<text top="446" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">life, liberty and personal security; VII, right to protection for mothers and children; IX, right to</text>
<text top="458" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">inviolability of the home, of the American Declaration; and to Articles 8(1) right to a fair trial;</text>
<text top="470" left="57" width="475" height="12" font="1">25(2) right to judicial protection, and 1(1) obligation to respect the rights, of the Convention. </text>
<text top="494" left="57" width="375" height="12" font="1">2. To transmit this report to the State of Suriname and to the petitioners. </text>
<text top="518" left="57" width="290" height="12" font="1">3. To continue with its analysis of the merits of the case. </text>
<text top="543" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">4. To make itself available to the parties with a view to reaching a friendly settlement of the</text>
<text top="555" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">matter  based on the respect to the rights recognized by the Convention and to invite  the</text>
<text top="567" left="57" width="287" height="12" font="1">parties of the case to answer about this possibility; and, </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="468" height="12" font="1">5. To publish this report and to include it in its Annual Report to the OAS General Assembly. </text>
<text top="616" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="1">Done and signed at the headquarters of the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights in</text>
<text top="628" left="57" width="205" height="12" font="1">the city of Washington, D.C., on the 7</text>
<text top="628" left="262" width="6" height="7" font="2">th</text>
<text top="628" left="268" width="270" height="12" font="1">  day of the month of March, 2000. (Signed:) Hélio</text>
<text top="640" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Bicudo,   Chairman;   Claudio   Grossman,   First   Vice-Chairman;   Juan   Méndez,   Second   Vice-</text>
<text top="652" left="57" width="481" height="12" font="1">Chairman; and Commissioners Marta Altolaguirre, Robert K. Goldman, Peter Laurie and Julio</text>
<text top="664" left="57" width="69" height="12" font="1">Prado Vallejo.</text>
<text top="802" left="296" width="4" height="7" font="2">6</text>
</page>
<outline>
<item page="1">II. PROCESSING BY THE COMMISSION</item>
<item page="1">III. POSITION OF THE PARTIES</item>
<item page="1">A. The petitioner</item>
<item page="3">IV. ANALYSIS OF ADMISSIBILITY</item>
<outline>
<item page="5">B. Other requirements for the admissibility of the petition</item>
</outline>
<item page="6">V. CONCLUSIONS</item>
</outline>
</pdf2xml>
