<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="23.12.0">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="0" size="10" family="IHOAJB+AdvTT153188ed" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="10" family="IHOBJI+AdvOTb0c9bf5d+20" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="12" family="IHOAJD+AdvTTec80583d.B" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="9" family="IHOELI+AdvPi1" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="9" family="IHOAJB+AdvTT153188ed" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="8" family="IHOBIH+AdvP1007BC" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="10" family="IHOBII+AdvHX" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="7" size="8" family="IHOAJF+AdvTTb6c2036d.I" color="#231f20"/>
	<fontspec id="8" size="8" family="IHOBJJ+AdvTTb6c2036d.I+20" color="#231f20"/>
<text top="95" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">Information regarding 10 process indicators representing five dimensions of quality and coordination of care was col-</text>
<text top="107" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">lected using interviews with staff and registered data. Indicators and dimensions had a particular focus on case-find-</text>
<text top="119" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">ing and case-management and coordination and collaboration between primary care and community services to</text>
<text top="131" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">support integrate services. Interviews with GPs and nurses in managing positions in primary care were matched</text>
<text top="143" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">with interviews with nurses at nearby community services to support triangulation and to gain additional information</text>
<text top="155" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">from a community perspective. Respondents were asked to provide examples where possible. In total, 24 semi-</text>
<text top="167" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">structured interviews were conducted by one of the authors (AHG) without prior knowledge about the level of utiliza-</text>
<text top="179" left="50" width="289" height="9" font="0">tion of hospital care among the eight providers. This principle of</text>
<text top="176" left="342" width="4" height="13" font="1">“</text>
<text top="179" left="347" width="33" height="9" font="0">blinded</text>
<text top="176" left="379" width="4" height="13" font="1">”</text>
<text top="179" left="387" width="164" height="9" font="0">interviews was performed to prevent</text>
<text top="191" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">bias in the collection and comparison on qualitative data. All interviews were audio taped enabling review by the</text>
<text top="203" left="50" width="45" height="9" font="0">co-author.</text>
<text top="221" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">Data from interviews were complemented with registered data used within a P4P scheme in primary care regarding</text>
<text top="233" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">continuity of care, number of medicines reviews to elderly 75+ and number of individualized care plans for elderly in</text>
<text top="245" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">home care. Based on the performance of these and other indicators, primary care providers in Region Skåne were</text>
<text top="257" left="50" width="244" height="9" font="0">able to generate up to 3% additional payments in 2012.</text>
<text top="275" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">Based on the collected data, differences between the eight practices were analysed in a ranking exercise. For each</text>
<text top="286" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">indicator, providers were assessed from one to three, where a higher value indicated a favourable position compared</text>
<text top="298" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">to other providers in the sample. The final assessment for each practice was communicated to interviewed GPs and</text>
<text top="310" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">nurses, who had the opportunity to comment and add or clarify information. Overall, the final assessment was</text>
<text top="322" left="50" width="43" height="9" font="0">accepted.</text>
<text top="340" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">Ranking of providers was compared with data from two outcome indicators reflecting utilization of hospital care: aver-</text>
<text top="352" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">age number of bed-days for patients 75+ with significant needs, and number of visits to hospital emergency units</text>
<text top="364" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">without hospitalization for patients 75+. These outcome indicators were used in Region Skåne for comparison of dif-</text>
<text top="376" left="50" width="419" height="9" font="0">ferent primary care providers. One of them (number of visits) was used within the P4P scheme.</text>
<text top="404" left="50" width="112" height="12" font="2">Regression models</text>
<text top="430" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">A quantitative approach was used to analyse the association between indicators of hospital utilization (outcome indi-</text>
<text top="442" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">cators) and a number of factors among all 150 primary care providers in Region Skåne reflecting both process indi-</text>
<text top="454" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">cators and non-controllable variables from the perspective of primary care providers. Registered data from year 2012</text>
<text top="466" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">were used in step-wise regression modelling. The same outcome indicators as in the ranking exercise were used as</text>
<text top="478" left="50" width="92" height="9" font="0">dependent variables:</text>
<text top="494" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="496" left="63" width="316" height="8" font="4">average number of bed-days for patients 75+ with significant health care needs;</text>
<text top="504" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="507" left="63" width="356" height="8" font="4">number of visits to hospital emergency units without hospitalization per 1000 patients 75+.</text>
<text top="524" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">Average, rather than median, in-patient days were used as most patients had not been admitted to hospital in-patient</text>
<text top="536" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">care at all. As the average is more sensitive to outliers, patients with 100 or more bed-days during the year were</text>
<text top="548" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">omitted from the analysis. Data related to avoidable hospitalization based on relevant diagnoses for this selected</text>
<text top="560" left="50" width="211" height="9" font="0">group of frail elderly patients were not available.</text>
<text top="578" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">Independent variables were chosen from registered data reflecting the same process indicators that were used in the</text>
<text top="590" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">qualitative study. An additional variable reflecting proportion of direct admissions to hospital wards (i.e. side-stepping</text>
<text top="602" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">the emergency intake at hospital) was also included. Most practices used this option to a limited degree and it was</text>
<text top="614" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">not relevant when comparing differences between the eight selected practices in the ranking exercise. Independent</text>
<text top="626" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">process variables were combined with other independent (control) variables reflecting location, ownership, health</text>
<text top="638" left="50" width="502" height="9" font="0">care needs and socio-economic status of registered individuals across providers. In total, eight independent vari-</text>
<text top="650" left="50" width="157" height="9" font="0">ables were included in the analysis:</text>
<text top="665" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="667" left="63" width="344" height="8" font="4">continuity (proportion of patients meeting the same GP during three consecutive visits);</text>
<text top="676" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="678" left="63" width="489" height="8" font="4">proportion of direct admissions from primary care or nursing homes to hospital wards (by-passing the hospital emergency</text>
<text top="689" left="63" width="24" height="8" font="4">units);</text>
<text top="698" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="700" left="63" width="489" height="8" font="4">number of medicines reviews in collaboration with pharmacist and community staff (in relation to number of elderly patients</text>
<text top="711" left="63" width="137" height="8" font="4">with significant health care needs);</text>
<text top="720" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="722" left="63" width="489" height="8" font="4">number of individualized care plans regarding care and social services established in collaboration between primary care and</text>
<text top="733" left="63" width="378" height="8" font="4">community services (in relation to number of elderly patients with significant health care needs);</text>
<text top="742" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="744" left="63" width="318" height="8" font="4">location of provider (five districts with different community and hospital services);</text>
<text top="753" left="50" width="4" height="12" font="3">.</text>
<text top="755" left="63" width="474" height="8" font="4">socio-economic status of registered individuals (measured through care need-index, CNI for each provider in May 2012)</text>
<text top="790" left="50" width="344" height="7" font="5">This article is published in a peer reviewed section of the International Journal of Integrated Care</text>
<text top="786" left="546" width="5" height="13" font="6">4</text>
<text top="59" left="50" width="148" height="8" font="7">International Journal of Integrated Care</text>
<text top="57" left="200" width="5" height="11" font="8">–</text>
<text top="59" left="208" width="96" height="8" font="7">Volume 14, 15 December</text>
<text top="57" left="307" width="5" height="11" font="8">–</text>
<text top="59" left="314" width="111" height="8" font="7">URN:NBN:NL:UI:10-1-114805</text>
<text top="57" left="429" width="5" height="11" font="8">–</text>
<text top="59" left="436" width="67" height="8" font="7"><a href="http://www.ijic.org/">http://www.ijic.org/</a></text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
