<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="23.08.0">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="792" width="612">
	<fontspec id="0" size="11" family="ABCDEE+Calibri" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="11" family="ABCDEE+Calibri,Bold" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="12" family="Times New Roman" color="#000000"/>
<text top="56" left="122" width="263" height="11" font="0">INTER  -  AMERICAN   COMMISSION  ON  HUMAN   RIGHTS </text>
<text top="69" left="122" width="264" height="11" font="0">COMISION  INTERAMERICANA  DE  DERECHOS   HUMANOS </text>
<text top="83" left="122" width="261" height="11" font="0">COMISSÃO   INTERAMERICANA  DE  DIREITOS   HUMANOS </text>
<text top="96" left="122" width="269" height="11" font="0">COMMISSION INTERAMÉRICAINE DES DROITS DE L'HOMME </text>
<text top="110" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="123" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="137" left="72" width="220" height="11" font="1"><b>ORGANIZACIÓN DE LOS ESTADOS AMERICANOS </b></text>
<text top="150" left="72" width="168" height="11" font="0">WASHINGTON, D.C. 2 0 0 0 6  E E U U </text>
<text top="163" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="177" left="540" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="190" left="468" width="73" height="11" font="0">March 17,  2014</text>
<text top="190" left="540" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="204" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="217" left="72" width="24" height="11" font="1"><b>Ref.: </b></text>
<text top="217" left="108" width="76" height="11" font="1"><b>Caso No. 12.816 </b></text>
<text top="217" left="396" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="217" left="432" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="217" left="468" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="217" left="504" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="231" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="231" left="108" width="162" height="11" font="1"><b>Adán Guillermo López Lone y otros </b></text>
<text top="244" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="244" left="108" width="49" height="11" font="1"><b>Honduras  </b></text>
<text top="257" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="271" left="72" width="66" height="11" font="0">Mr. Secretary: </text>
<text top="284" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="298" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="298" left="108" width="435" height="11" font="0">I am pleased to address  you on behalf of the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights  in </text>
<text top="311" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">order to file Case No. 12.816 Adán Guillermo López Lone et al. v. Honduras (hereinafter “the State”, “the </text>
<text top="325" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">Honduran  State”  or  “Honduras”)  before  the  jurisdiction  of  the  Honorable  Inter-American  Court  of </text>
<text top="338" left="72" width="67" height="11" font="0">Human  Rights.</text>
<text top="338" left="139" width="3" height="11" font="2"> </text>
<text top="338" left="144" width="399" height="11" font="0">The  instant  case  involves  the  disciplinary  proceedings  against  judges  Adán  Guillermo </text>
<text top="352" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">López  Lone,  Luis  Alonso  Chévez  de  la  Rocha  and  Ramón  Enrique  Barrios  Maldonado,  as  well  as </text>
<text top="365" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">magistrate Tirza del Carmen Flores Lanza, within the context of the coup that took place in Honduras in </text>
<text top="378" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">June 2009. The victims were members of the “Association Judges for Democracy” which published press </text>
<text top="392" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">releases describing the facts related to the dismissal of former President Zelaya as a coup, in opposition </text>
<text top="405" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">to  the  official  version  of  the  Supreme  Court  of  Justice,  which  argued  that  it  was  a  constitutional </text>
<text top="419" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">succession. The Commission concluded that the disciplinary proceedings were initiated with the aim of </text>
<text top="432" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">sanctioning  acts  or  expressions  of  the  victims  against  the  coup.  The  Commission  also  noted  that  the </text>
<text top="446" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">proceedings  were  carried  out  in  violation  of  the  procedure  established  in  the  Constitution  which </text>
<text top="459" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">provided that the Supreme Court of Justice was the competent authority to decide on the dismissal of </text>
<text top="472" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">the  judges  “after  the  proposal  of  the  Consejo  de  la  Carrera  Judicial”.  In  opposition  to  that  norm,  the </text>
<text top="486" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">dismissal  took  place  by  means  of  agreements  of  the  Supreme  Court  of  Justice  and  the  Consejo  de  la </text>
<text top="499" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Carrera  Judicial  only  intervened  after  the  decision  of  the  Supreme  Court  of  Justice,  as  an  appeal </text>
<text top="513" left="72" width="313" height="11" font="0">authority, despite such council was dependent of the Supreme Court. </text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="539" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="539" left="108" width="434" height="11" font="0">The  Commission  also  found  irregularities  that  affected  other  components  of  due  process.  For </text>
<text top="553" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">example, the Supreme Court did not act as an impartial authority, provided that its public positions of </text>
<text top="566" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">legitimate  the  coup.  Neither  the  victims  had  the  opportunity  to  present  a  disqualification  of  the </text>
<text top="580" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">members  of  the  Consejo  de  la  Carrera  Judicial  who  were  called  to  act  on  the  council  directly  by  its </text>
<text top="593" left="72" width="304" height="11" font="0">president, with no previous process to guarantee its independence. </text>
<text top="607" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="620" left="72" width="18" height="11" font="0">Mr. </text>
<text top="634" left="72" width="167" height="11" font="0">Pablo Saavedra Alessandri, Secretary </text>
<text top="647" left="72" width="174" height="11" font="0">Inter-American Court of Human Rights </text>
<text top="660" left="72" width="95" height="11" font="0">Apartado 6906-1000 </text>
<text top="674" left="72" width="91" height="11" font="0">San José, Costa Rica </text>
<text top="687" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="701" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="792" width="612">
	<fontspec id="3" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Calibri" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="10" family="Arial" color="#000000"/>
<text top="56" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="56" left="108" width="434" height="11" font="0">Moreover, the  Commission found that the disciplinary  grounds applied to the victims violated </text>
<text top="69" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">the principle of legality and that the decisions adopted were not motivated. Therefore, the Commission </text>
<text top="83" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">found that the decision violated the right to freedom of expression. Such intervention of the disciplinary </text>
<text top="96" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">institutions  of  the  State  was  directed  also  to  obstruct  the  victim’s  participation  in  the  “Association </text>
<text top="110" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Judges for Democracy” as a result of their opposition to the coup. In that regard, the State also violated </text>
<text top="123" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">the political rights and the freedom of association respectively. Finally, as a result of the decision of the </text>
<text top="137" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Consejo de la Carrera Judicial, the victims did not receive effective judicial protection and did not obtain </text>
<text top="150" left="72" width="53" height="11" font="0">reparation. </text>
<text top="163" left="108" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="177" left="108" width="434" height="11" font="0">The State of Honduras ratified the American Convention on Human Rights on September 8, 1977 </text>
<text top="190" left="72" width="349" height="11" font="0">and accepted the contentious jurisdiction of the Court on September 9, 1981. </text>
<text top="204" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="217" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="217" left="108" width="435" height="11" font="0">The Commission has designated Commissioner Tracy Robinson, Emilio Álvarez Icaza L., executive </text>
<text top="231" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">secretary,  and  the  Special  Rapporteur  for  the  freedom  of  speech  Catalina  Botero,  as  its  delegate. </text>
<text top="244" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">Likewise,  Elizabeth  Abi-Mershed,  Deputy  Executive  Secretary,  Silvia  Serrano  Guzmán  Jorge  H.  Meza </text>
<text top="257" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Flores  and  Ona  Flores,  attorneys  of  the  Executive  Secretariat  of  the  IACHR,  have  been  designated  to </text>
<text top="271" left="72" width="104" height="11" font="0">serve as legal advisors. </text>
<text top="284" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="298" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="298" left="108" width="435" height="11" font="0">In  accordance  with  Article  35  of  the  Rules  of  Procedure  of  the  Inter-American  Court,  the </text>
<text top="311" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Commission is enclosing a copy of Merits Report No. 103/13, prepared in compliance with Article 50 of </text>
<text top="325" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">the  American  Convention,  as  well  as  a  copy  of  the  entire  file  before  the  Inter-American  Commission </text>
<text top="338" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">(Appendix  I.)  and  the  attachments  used  to  prepare  the  Report  on  the  Merits  (Attachment).  The </text>
<text top="352" left="72" width="356" height="11" font="0">Commission transmitted the Merits Report to the State on December 17, 2013. </text>
<text top="365" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="378" left="108" width="434" height="11" font="0">The Report was transmitted to the State granting it two months to provide information on the </text>
<text top="392" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">measures adopted in compliance with the recommendations. Mediante comunicación recibida el 17 de </text>
<text top="405" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">febrero de 2014, el Estado hondureño presentó un escrito en el cual hizo referencia a los artículos 50 y </text>
<text top="419" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">51 de la Convención Americana y a una supuesta falta de claridad de su texto. El Estado también indicó </text>
<text top="432" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">que las conclusiones de la Comisión fueron sesgadas. El Estado hizo referencia genérica al mecanismo de </text>
<text top="446" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">solución  amistosa  y  finalmente  señaló  que  no  se  habían  agotado  los  recursos  internos.  El  Estado  no </text>
<text top="459" left="72" width="395" height="11" font="0">presentó ninguna información concreta sobre el cumplimiento de las recomendaciones. </text>
<text top="472" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="486" left="108" width="434" height="11" font="0">Taking  into  account  the  aforementioned,  the  Commission  submits  the  case  before  the </text>
<text top="499" left="72" width="366" height="11" font="0">jurisdiction of the Court for the need to obtain justice for the victims of this case.  </text>
<text top="513" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="526" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="435" height="11" font="0">En  virtud  de  lo  anterior,  la  CIDH  solicita  a  la  Corte  que  concluya  y  declare  que  el  Estado  de </text>
<text top="539" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">Honduras  es  responsable  por  la  violación  de  los  derechos  a  las  garantías  judiciales,  al  principio  de </text>
<text top="553" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">legalidad,  libertad  de  expresión,  libertad  de  asociación,  derechos  políticos  y  a  la  protección  judicial, </text>
<text top="566" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">consagrados  en  los  artículos  8,  9,  13,  16,  23  y  25  de  la  Convención  Americana,  en  relación  con  las </text>
<text top="580" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">obligaciones  establecidas en  los  artículos  1.1  y  2  del  mismo  instrumento,  en perjuicio  del  señor  Adán </text>
<text top="593" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Guillermo López Lone, Ramón Enrique Barrios Maldonado, Luis Alonso Chévez de la Rocha y la señora </text>
<text top="607" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">Tirza del Carmen Flores Lanza. Asimismo, que el Estado de Honduras es responsable por la violación al </text>
<text top="620" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">derecho de reunión consagrado en el artículo 15 de la Convención en relación con los artículos 1.1 y 2 </text>
<text top="634" left="72" width="337" height="11" font="0">del mismo instrumento, en perjuicio del señor Adán Guillermo López Lone. </text>
<text top="647" left="108" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="660" left="107" width="435" height="11" font="0">La  Comisión  considera  necesario  que  en  el  presente  caso  la  Corte  Interamericana  ordene  las </text>
<text top="674" left="72" width="155" height="11" font="0">siguientes medidas de reparación: </text>
<text top="687" left="72" width="2" height="10" font="3"> </text>
<text top="699" left="108" width="8" height="10" font="3">1.</text>
<text top="700" left="116" width="3" height="9" font="4"> </text>
<text top="699" left="126" width="380" height="10" font="3">Reincorporar a las víctimas al Poder Judicial, en un cargo similar al que desempeñaban, con </text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="398" height="10" font="3">la misma remuneración, beneficios sociales y rango equiparables a los que les correspondería el </text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="792" width="612">
<text top="56" left="108" width="398" height="10" font="3">día de hoy si no hubieran sido destituidos, por el plazo de tiempo que quedaba pendiente de su </text>
<text top="68" left="108" width="398" height="10" font="3">mandato. Si por razones fundadas no es posible la reincorporación, el Estado deberá pagar una </text>
<text top="80" left="108" width="112" height="10" font="3">indemnización alternativa.  </text>
<text top="93" left="108" width="2" height="10" font="3"> </text>
<text top="105" left="108" width="8" height="10" font="3">2.</text>
<text top="105" left="116" width="3" height="9" font="4"> </text>
<text top="105" left="126" width="380" height="10" font="3">Reparar  las  consecuencias  de  las  violaciones  declaradas  en  el  informe,  incluyendo  tanto  el </text>
<text top="117" left="108" width="165" height="10" font="3">daño material como el daño inmaterial.  </text>
<text top="129" left="72" width="2" height="10" font="3"> </text>
<text top="141" left="108" width="8" height="10" font="3">3.</text>
<text top="142" left="116" width="3" height="9" font="4"> </text>
<text top="141" left="126" width="380" height="10" font="3">Disponer  las  modificaciones  normativas  necesarias  para  asegurar  que  los  procesos </text>
<text top="154" left="108" width="398" height="10" font="3">disciplinarios contra jueces y juezas sean realizados por autoridades competentes y con garantías </text>
<text top="166" left="108" width="188" height="10" font="3">suficientes de independencia e imparcialidad. </text>
<text top="178" left="108" width="2" height="10" font="3"> </text>
<text top="196" left="108" width="8" height="10" font="3">4.</text>
<text top="197" left="116" width="3" height="9" font="4"> </text>
<text top="196" left="126" width="380" height="10" font="3">Disponer  las  modificaciones  normativas  necesarias  para  asegurar  que  las  causales </text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="398" height="10" font="3">disciplinarias de jueces y juezas y las sanciones aplicables, sean compatibles con el principio de </text>
<text top="221" left="108" width="225" height="10" font="3">legalidad, en los términos desarrollados en el informe.  </text>
<text top="233" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="246" left="108" width="432" height="11" font="0">Apart from the need to obtain justice, the Commission considers the case raises issues of Inter-</text>
<text top="260" left="72" width="117" height="11" font="0">American public interest.  </text>
<text top="273" left="108" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="287" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="287" left="108" width="434" height="11" font="0">Específicamente,  el  presente  caso  permitirá  a  la  Corte  profundizar  su  jurisprudencia  sobre  el </text>
<text top="300" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">principio de independencia judicial y sus implicaciones en las garantías reforzadas de legalidad y debido </text>
<text top="314" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">proceso en  el marco  de  un  proceso sancionatorio en  perjuicio  de  un  juez o  jueza.  Particularmente,  el </text>
<text top="327" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">presente  caso  ofrece  a  la  Corte  Interamericana  la  posibilidad  de  analizar  la  importancia  que  tiene  el </text>
<text top="340" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">respeto de tales garantías a la luz del principio de independencia judicial en un contexto de  una crisis </text>
<text top="354" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">democrática  resultante  de  un  golpe  de  Estado.  Por  otra  parte,  la  Corte  podrá  profundizar  su </text>
<text top="367" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">jurisprudencia  en  materia  de  responsabilidades  ulteriores  al  ejercicio  de  la  libertad  de  expresión, </text>
<text top="381" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">específicamente en cuanto al requisito de estricta legalidad cuando se trata de causales disciplinaria, así </text>
<text top="394" left="72" width="454" height="11" font="0">como a la manera en que deben aplicarse los requisitos de idoneidad, necesidad y proporcionalidad.  </text>
<text top="408" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="421" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="421" left="108" width="435" height="11" font="0">Inasmuch  as  these  issues  have  a  consequential  effect  on  Inter-American  public  order,  as </text>
<text top="434" left="72" width="470" height="11" font="0">provided  under  Article  35.1.f  of  the  Rules  of  Procedure  of  the  Inter-American  Court,  the  Commission </text>
<text top="448" left="72" width="183" height="11" font="0">proffers the following expert witnesses:  </text>
<text top="461" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="475" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">1.  xxxxxxxxxxxx,  who  will  provide  testimony  on  due  process  guarantees  and  the  principle  of </text>
<text top="488" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">legality  within  the  ambit  of  a  disciplinary  proceeding  of  dismissal  of  a  judge  in  light  of  the </text>
<text top="502" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">principle of judicial independence, taking into account both, the international standards and the </text>
<text top="515" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">developments in comparative law. In particular, the expert will mention the implications of the </text>
<text top="528" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">respect of such guarantees in the context of democratic crisis such as a coup. Finally, the expert </text>
<text top="542" left="104" width="188" height="11" font="0">will analyze the specific facts of the case.  </text>
<text top="555" left="104" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="569" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">2.  xxxxxxxxxxx, who will provide testimony on the requirements to be taken into consideration </text>
<text top="582" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">when analyzing the subsequent responsibility within a disciplinary proceeding as the one carried </text>
<text top="596" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">out  in  the  instant  case.  Specifically,  the  expert  will  analyze  the  principle  of  strict  legality  when </text>
<text top="609" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">disciplinary  grounds  are  used  in  order  to  impose  a  subsequent  responsibility,  as  well  as  the </text>
<text top="622" left="104" width="314" height="11" font="0">application of the criteria of suitability, necessity and proportionality.  </text>
<text top="636" left="104" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="649" left="104" width="439" height="11" font="0">3.  The  Commission  requests  the  transfer  of  the  expert  witness  declaration  on  Param </text>
<text top="663" left="104" width="323" height="11" font="0">Cumaraswamy in the case Quintana Coello y otros vs. Ecuador (12.600). </text>
<text top="676" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="690" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="703" left="107" width="435" height="11" font="0">Conjuntamente  con  los  anexos  al  Informe  103/13,  la  Comisión  remitirá  el  CV  de  los/las </text>
<text top="716" left="72" width="117" height="11" font="0">peritos/as propuestos/as. </text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="792" width="612">
	<fontspec id="5" size="11" family="ABCDEE+Calibri" color="#a6a6a6"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="11" family="ABCDEE+Calibri,Italic" color="#a6a6a6"/>
<text top="56" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="69" left="107" width="435" height="11" font="0">Finally, the petitioners expressed the victims’ interest in the submission of the present case to </text>
<text top="83" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">the Inter-American Court and informed that the following shall be representatives of the victims:  the </text>
<text top="96" left="72" width="471" height="11" font="0">Asociación  Jueces  por  la Democracia and  the  Centro  por  la  Justicia  y el  Derecho  Internacional  (CEJIL). </text>
<text top="110" left="72" width="225" height="11" font="0">Their email is: xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx </text>
<text top="123" left="306" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="137" left="306" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="150" left="306" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="108" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="144" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="180" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="216" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="252" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="163" left="288" width="2" height="11" font="5"> </text>
<text top="163" left="324" width="2" height="11" font="5"> </text>
<text top="163" left="360" width="101" height="11" font="6"><i>Signed in the original   </i></text>
<text top="177" left="72" width="2" height="11" font="0"> </text>
<text top="177" left="360" width="92" height="11" font="0">Mario López Garelli  </text>
<text top="190" left="72" width="434" height="11" font="0">                                                                                                By authorization of the Executive Secretary </text>
<text top="204" left="72" width="3" height="11" font="2"> </text>
<text top="218" left="72" width="3" height="11" font="2"> </text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
