<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="23.08.0">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="0" size="6" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="801" left="296" width="6" height="8" font="0">1 </text>
<text top="57" left="247" width="105" height="12" font="1"><b>REPORT Nº 43/98 </b></text>
<text top="69" left="265" width="70" height="12" font="2">CASE 11.816 </text>
<text top="81" left="256" width="86" height="12" font="2">HANIFF HILAIRE </text>
<text top="93" left="236" width="127" height="12" font="2">TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO </text>
<text top="105" left="246" width="108" height="12" font="2">September 25, 1998 </text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="130" left="57" width="13" height="12" font="1"><b>I. </b></text>
<text top="130" left="92" width="83" height="12" font="1"><b>BACKGROUND </b></text>
<text top="156" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">1.  By  fax  dated  October  7,  1997,  the  London  firm  of  solicitors,  Simmons  &amp;  Simmons, </text>
<text top="168" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">presented  a  petition  to  the  Inter-American  Commission  on  Human  Rights  (hereinafter  &#34;the </text>
<text top="180" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Commission&#34;)  against  the  Republic  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  (hereinafter  &#34;the  State&#34;  or </text>
<text top="192" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">&#34;Trinidad&#34;)  on  behalf  of  Mr.  Haniff  Hilaire,  presently  under  sentence  of  death  at  the  State </text>
<text top="204" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Prison in Port of Spain. The petition stated that the High Court of Trinidad at the Port of Spain </text>
<text top="216" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Assizes tried the Applicant for the murder of Mr. Alexander Jordan on February 13, 1991 along </text>
<text top="229" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">with two co-defendants, Ms. Indravani Ramjattan and Mr. Denny Baptiste. The Applicant was </text>
<text top="241" left="57" width="442" height="12" font="2">convicted on May 29, 1995 and sentenced to the mandatory death penalty for murder. </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">2.  Simultaneous  with  the  presentation  of  the  complaint,  the  Applicant  requested  the </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Commission to issue precautionary measures, pursuant to article 29(2) of its Regulations, and </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">to seek a stay of execution pending the determination of the complaint by the Commission. On </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">October  16,  1997,  the  Commission  requested  the  State  to  stay  Mr.  Hilaire's  execution  &#34;until </text>
<text top="316" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">such  time  as  the  Commission  has  had  the  opportunity  to  consider  this  case  and  issue  its </text>
<text top="328" left="57" width="429" height="12" font="2">decision.&#34; The Commission requested &#34;an immediate consent to the above request.&#34; </text>
<text top="354" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">3.  The  State  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  did  not  respond  to  this  request  for  precautionary </text>
<text top="366" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">measures.  The  Commission  regrets  that  the  State  party  was  not  prepared  to  grant  the </text>
<text top="378" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">precautionary measures requested under article 29(2) of its Regulations, and to guarantee that </text>
<text top="391" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the Petitioner would not be executed while his case was under examination. In fact, however, </text>
<text top="403" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">as  of  September  25,  1998,  the  petitioner  has  not  been  executed.  The  Commission  observes </text>
<text top="415" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">that it is not for the State party, but for the Commission, to decide whether or not a complaint </text>
<text top="427" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">is  admissible.  The  Commission  requests  the  State  to  cooperate  fully  with  the  Commission's </text>
<text top="439" left="57" width="234" height="12" font="2">examination of communications in the future. </text>
<text top="465" left="57" width="18" height="12" font="1"><b>II. </b></text>
<text top="465" left="92" width="239" height="12" font="1"><b>PROCEEDINGS BEFORE THE COMMISSION </b></text>
<text top="491" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">4.  Mr.  Hilaire's  appeal  to  the  Court  of  Appeal  of  the  Republic  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  was </text>
<text top="504" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">dismissed  on  November  7,  1996.  On  October  3,  1997,  the  Applicant's  counsel  in  London </text>
<text top="516" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">advised him that a petition for special leave to appeal to the Privy Council stood no reasonable </text>
<text top="528" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">prospect  of  success.  On  November 6, 1997 the  Applicant  was  refused  leave to  appeal to the </text>
<text top="540" left="57" width="204" height="12" font="2">Judicial Committee of the Privy Council. </text>
<text top="566" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">5. The complaint alleges that the following articles of the American Convention were violated </text>
<text top="578" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">by the State of Trinidad and Tobago to the detriment of the Applicant: Articles 5, 7 and 8 of </text>
<text top="591" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the  American  Convention  on  Human  Rights  (hereinafter  &#34;the  Convention&#34;  or  &#34;the  American </text>
<text top="603" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Convention&#34;).  On  December  19,  1997,  a  Supplementary  Petition  was  filed  on  behalf  of  Mr. </text>
<text top="615" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Haniff Hilaire by Simmons &amp; Simmons. Specifically, the petitioners allege serious violations as </text>
<text top="627" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">regards the right to legal representation in a capital case. The petition alleges, <i>inter alia</i>, that </text>
<text top="639" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">&#34;the  police  fabricated  evidence  against  the  Victim  [Hilaire]:  the  victim  claims  that  he  knew </text>
<text top="651" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">nothing  about  the  deceased,  Alexander  Jordan,  until  he  was  questioned  by  the  police.&#34;  In </text>
<text top="663" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">addition,  the  petition  alleges  that  Hilaire  was  &#34;detained  in  custody  as  an  accused  person </text>
<text top="675" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">awaiting trial for over 4 years, from 19 February 1991 until 09 May 1995, &#34;in violation of his </text>
<text top="688" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">right  to  be  tried  within  a  reasonable  time.&#34;  Further,  the  petition  alleges  that  Hilaire  had </text>
<text top="700" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">inadequate time to prepare his defense, and that he was able &#34;to see his attorney only for a </text>
<text top="712" left="57" width="200" height="12" font="2">few minutes each day during the trial.&#34; </text>
<text top="738" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">6.  The State  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  responded  to the  petition  by  Note  POL:6/16/2  Vol.  5  of </text>
<text top="750" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">December  15,  1997.  In  this  Note,  the  State  informed  the  Commission  that  the  &#34;Instructions </text>
<text top="763" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Relating to  Applications  from  Persons under Sentence  of  Death issued  by the Government  of </text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="4" size="7" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="13" family="AAAAAJ+TimesNewRomanPSMT" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="7" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="7" size="5" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="8" size="8" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="801" left="296" width="6" height="8" font="0">2 </text>
<text top="57" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Trinidad and Tobago on 13 October 1997, are deemed to apply to the communication of Mr. </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="365" height="12" font="2">Haniff Hilaire. Case No 11.816.&#34; In addition, the State pointed out that: </text>
<text top="95" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">... in order for any recommendation by  the Commission to be considered  by the Minister of National Security  when </text>
<text top="104" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">advising  his  Excellency  the  President  of  the  exercise  of  the  prerogative  of  mercy,  the  Government  of  Trinidad  and </text>
<text top="113" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Tobago  respectfully  requests  the  Commission  to  submit  its  determination  in  respect  of  the  communication  within  a </text>
<text top="123" left="92" width="328" height="9" font="4">period of six months from the date of the despatch of the response by the State party.</text>
<text top="118" left="420" width="3" height="15" font="5"> </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">In other words, the State requested that the Commission issue a decision on the merits in this </text>
<text top="158" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">case within a period of six months from December 15, 1997 or by June 15, 1998. According to </text>
<text top="170" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the  State,  the  decision  of  the  Commission  would  be  considered  by  the  Minister  of  National </text>
<text top="182" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Security  when  advising  the  President  as  to  whether  he  should  exercise  the  prerogative  of </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">mercy. Unlike other systems where the prerogative of mercy is considered part of the domestic </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">process,  in  Trinidad  and  Tobago  the  international  instance  is  used  to  inform  the  domestic </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="45" height="12" font="2">process. </text>
<text top="245" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">7. The Inter-American Commission on Human Rights, at the request of the Government, held a </text>
<text top="257" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">meeting  on  February  20,  1998,  during  its  98th  period  of  sessions,  with  Mr.  Ralph  Maraj, </text>
<text top="269" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Trinidad and Tobago and Mr. Ramesh L. Maharaj, </text>
<text top="281" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the  Attorney  General  of  that  State.  In  his  statement,  the  Attorney  General  argued  that  the </text>
<text top="293" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">&#34;Commission has no power to challenge the implementation of a sentence of death imposed by </text>
<text top="305" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">a  court  of  competent  jurisdiction  in  Trinidad  and  Tobago.&#34;  The  argument  of  the  State  is  as </text>
<text top="318" left="57" width="43" height="12" font="2">follows: </text>
<text top="344" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Under the Convention, the Commission has the power to make recommendations to the State Party, but in so far as </text>
<text top="353" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">those recommendations relate to a sentence imposed by the courts of the State Party it would be acting <i>ultra vires</i> if </text>
<text top="362" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">it attempted to alter by its recommendations the domestic law of the State in respect of sentencing. The Commission </text>
<text top="371" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">therefore  has  no  power  to  challenge  the  implementation  of  a  sentence  of  death  imposed  by  a  court  of  competent </text>
<text top="380" left="92" width="133" height="9" font="4">jurisdiction in Trinidad and Tobago.</text>
<text top="376" left="225" width="3" height="15" font="5"> </text>
<text top="403" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">The Constitution of Trinidad and Tobago mandates all arms of the State, including the Judicial arm, to uphold the law </text>
<text top="412" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">of  Trinidad  and  Tobago.  The  State  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  therefore  has  a  mandatory  obligation  to  ensure  that  its </text>
<text top="422" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Constitution and laws are not undermined, subverted or frustrated in their operation. It was for this reason that the </text>
<text top="431" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Government  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago,  by  its  reservation  entered  when  accepting  the  compulsory  jurisdiction  of  the </text>
<text top="440" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Inter-American  Court  of  Human  Rights,  stated  that  the  Court  can  only  have  jurisdiction  to  the  extent  that  it  is </text>
<text top="449" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">consistent with the Constitution of Trinidad and Tobago. The Commission therefore does not have jurisdiction either </text>
<text top="458" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">by its acts or omissions to prevent in any way a sentence, authorized  by the Constitution and laws of Trinidad and </text>
<text top="467" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Tobago and pronounced by a court of competent jurisdiction, from being carried into effect. <i>It is therefore open for </i></text>
<text top="476" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="6"><i>the  Government  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago,  whilst  a  petition  is  pending  before  the  Commission,  to  carry  out  the </i></text>
<text top="485" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="6"><i>sentence of death once the time stipulated in accordance with the Constitution and laws of Trinidad and Tobago has </i></text>
<text top="495" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="6"><i>expired</i>. The Commission may recommend the award of compensation to a victim. It may recommend that the State </text>
<text top="504" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">Party correct those matters which gave rise to a substantive breach so that others do not suffer the same violation in </text>
<text top="513" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">future. However it is submitted that the Commission, either directly or by its recommendation, has no power to alter </text>
<text top="522" left="92" width="286" height="9" font="4">the lawful sentence imposed by a court of a State Party. (Emphasis added).</text>
<text top="518" left="379" width="3" height="15" font="5"> </text>
<text top="545" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">8.  An  article  published in the  Trinidad  Express  on  March  13,  1998  stated the  Ministry  of the </text>
<text top="557" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Attorney General had issued a press release to the effect that &#34;the six-month period in respect </text>
<text top="569" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">to  their  [Tony  Briggs  and  Wenceslaus  James] applications  to the  Inter-American  Commission </text>
<text top="581" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">on  Human  Rights  expires  on  June  11,  1998,  and  after  this  date  the  state  will  decide  what </text>
<text top="594" left="57" width="290" height="12" font="2">action it will take in respect to the two condemned men.&#34;</text>
<text top="593" left="347" width="4" height="8" font="0">1</text>
<text top="594" left="351" width="192" height="12" font="2"> This article gave the impression that </text>
<text top="606" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Briggs and James would be the first two prisoners to be hanged by the State of Trinidad and </text>
<text top="618" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Tobago. The same article also stated that &#34;[F]ollowing Briggs and James there are three other </text>
<text top="630" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Death Row inmates listed to be executed soon after. They are Anthony Garcia and Anderson </text>
<text top="642" left="57" width="153" height="12" font="2">Noel and Christopher Bethel.&#34; </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">9. As a result of the above-mentioned meeting on February 20, 1998, the Commission decided </text>
<text top="681" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">to request provisional measures from the Court in the cases of James, Briggs, Noel, Garcia and </text>
<text top="693" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Bethel.  The  Commission,  during  its  99th  (Extraordinary)  meeting  approved  the  text  of  this </text>
<text top="705" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">request  and  on  May  22,  1998,  the  Commission  formally  requested  provisional  measures  in </text>
<text top="717" left="57" width="66" height="12" font="2">those cases. </text>
<text top="749" left="57" width="148" height="12" font="2">                                         </text>
<text top="761" left="57" width="3" height="6" font="7">1</text>
<text top="762" left="60" width="415" height="10" font="8"> Ucill Cambridge, &#34;Sledgehammer killers first to go on Death Row,&#34; Trinidad Express, March 13, 1998. </text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="801" left="296" width="6" height="8" font="0">3 </text>
<text top="57" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">10. On May 27, 1998, the President of the Inter-American Court granted Provisional Measures </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">in the cases of James, Briggs, Noel, Garcia and Bethel, and decided to require the Republic of </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Trinidad  and  Tobago  &#34;to  take  all  measures  necessary  to  preserve  the  lives  of  Wenceslaus </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">James,  Anthony  Briggs,  Anderson  Noel,  Anthony  Garcia  and  Christopher  Bethel,  so  that  the </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="2">Court  may  examine  the  pertinence  of  the  provisional  measures  requested  by  the  Inter-</text>
<text top="117" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">American Commission on Human Rights.&#34; On June 14, 1998, the Court, in plenary, ratified the </text>
<text top="130" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">President's  action  and  ordered  &#34;Trinidad  and  Tobago  to  take  all  measures  necessary  to </text>
<text top="142" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">preserve the life and physical integrity of Wenceslaus James, Anthony Briggs, Anderson Noel, </text>
<text top="154" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Anthony Garcia and Christopher Bethel, so as not to hinder the processing of their cases before </text>
<text top="166" left="57" width="147" height="12" font="2">the Inter-American system.&#34; </text>
<text top="192" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">11. On March 25, 1998 the State presented its response to the Supplementary Petition filed by </text>
<text top="204" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the petitioners on February 25, 1998. In this response the State noted that &#34;in order for any </text>
<text top="216" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">recommendation  by  the  Commission  to  be  considered  by  the  Minister  of  National  Security </text>
<text top="229" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">when  advising  His  Excellency  the  President  on  the  exercise  of  the  prerogative  of  mercy,  the </text>
<text top="241" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Government  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  respectfully  requests  the  Commission  to  submit  its </text>
<text top="253" left="57" width="416" height="12" font="2">determination in respect of this supplementary communication by 11 June 1998.&#34; </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">12. On July 10, 1998, the petitioners informed the Commission that on July 9, 1998 a Warrant </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">of Execution was read to Mr. Haniff Hilaire and the execution was scheduled for Tuesday, July </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">14, 1998. In the opinion of the petitioners, since the Instructions were approved on October 9, </text>
<text top="316" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">1997, two days after Mr. Hilaire's petition was filed with the Commission, on October 7, 1997, </text>
<text top="328" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">then the Instructions, if valid, did not apply to the Applicant. Further, the petitioners requested </text>
<text top="340" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the  Commission  to  ask  the  Court  to  order  provisional  measures,  pursuant to  Article  63(2)  of </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="255" height="12" font="2">the Convention, to preserve the life of Mr. Hilaire. </text>
<text top="378" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">13. On July 10, 1998, the Commission requested the Court to amplify the provisional measures </text>
<text top="391" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">ordered on May 27, 1998 and ratified on June 14, 1998 in favor of Wenceslaus James, et al. to </text>
<text top="403" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">include  Mr.  Haniff  Hilaire.  By  Order  of  the  President  of  the  Court  dated  July  13,  1998,  Mr. </text>
<text top="415" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Hilaire  was  included  in the earlier  Order  and  the  Court  decided  &#34;[T]o  require the  Republic  of </text>
<text top="427" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Trinidad  and  Tobago  to  take  all measures necessary to  preserve  the  life  of Haniff  Hilaire,  so </text>
<text top="439" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">that the Court may examine the pertinence of the request of the Inter-American Commission </text>
<text top="451" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">on  Human  Rights  to  amplify  the  provisional  measures  adopted  in  the  James,  Briggs,  Noel, </text>
<text top="463" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Garcia  and  Bethel  cases.&#34;  On  August  29,  1998,  the  full  Court  ratified  the  President's  Order </text>
<text top="476" left="57" width="108" height="12" font="2">dated July 13, 1998. </text>
<text top="502" left="57" width="198" height="12" font="1"><b>III.  GENERAL CONSIDERATIONS </b></text>
<text top="528" left="57" width="15" height="12" font="1"><b>A. </b></text>
<text top="528" left="92" width="177" height="12" font="1"><b>The Commission's Competence</b> </text>
<text top="554" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">14. Trinidad and Tobago is a State party to the American Convention, having ratified the treaty </text>
<text top="566" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">on  May 28,  1991.  The  petition  alleges  violations  of human  rights  set forth in  the  Convention </text>
<text top="578" left="57" width="239" height="12" font="2">which the Commission is competent to review. </text>
<text top="604" left="57" width="15" height="12" font="1"><b>B. </b></text>
<text top="604" left="92" width="224" height="12" font="1"><b>Procedural Admissibility of the Petition </b></text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>1. </b></text>
<text top="631" left="92" width="194" height="12" font="1"><b>Exhaustion of Domestic Remedies</b> </text>
<text top="657" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">15. The Government of Trinidad and Tobago stated in its response dated December 15, 1997 </text>
<text top="669" left="57" width="28" height="12" font="2">that: </text>
<text top="695" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">In the interests of expediency (...) notwithstanding the failure of the Applicant to first seek redress for his grievances </text>
<text top="704" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">by  way  of  a  Constitutional  Motion  before  the  domestic  courts  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago,  except  as  herein  expressly </text>
<text top="713" left="92" width="449" height="9" font="4">provided, the State party raises no challenge to the admissibility of this communication based on the exhaustion of </text>
<text top="723" left="92" width="108" height="9" font="4">domestic remedies rule (...).</text>
<text top="718" left="200" width="3" height="15" font="5"> </text>
<text top="746" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">16. The petitioners, in the observations to the response of the State Party, dated February 25, </text>
<text top="758" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">1998,  noted  that  &#34;the  State  Party  has  raised  no  challenge  to  the  admissibility  of  this </text>
<text top="770" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">communication based on the `exhaustion of domestic remedies rule.' However, the State Party </text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="801" left="296" width="6" height="8" font="0">4 </text>
<text top="57" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">has suggested that the victim should first have sought redress for his grievances by way of a </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Constitutional Motion before the domestic courts of Trinidad and Tobago. For the avoidance of </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">doubt  we  submit that,  since  legal  aid  is not  available  for  a  constitutional  Motion, this  should </text>
<text top="93" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">not  be  regarded  as  an  available  remedy  under  domestic  law  for  the  purposes  of  Article </text>
<text top="105" left="57" width="329" height="12" font="2">46(1)(a) of the Convention or of Article 37(1) of the Regulations.</text>
<text top="105" left="385" width="4" height="8" font="0">2</text>
<text top="105" left="389" width="4" height="12" font="2"> </text>
<text top="132" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">17. The jurisprudence of the Inter-American Commission and Court supports the view that a </text>
<text top="144" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">remedy  needs to  be  effective  and capable  of  producing the  result  for  which  it  was  designed, </text>
<text top="156" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">and  that  it  is  not  sufficient  for  the  remedy  simply  to  be  available.  (Velásquez </text>
<text top="168" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Rodríguez,Preliminary  Objections.  Judgment  of  June  26,  1987,  para.  88).  For  an  indigent </text>
<text top="180" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">prisoner, who has exhausted all judicial appeals including recourse to the Judicial Committee of </text>
<text top="192" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the Privy Council in London, to be expected to file a constitutional motion, the burden of proof </text>
<text top="204" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">lies  with the State to  show  that this  remedy  is  effective  and capable  of  producing the  result </text>
<text top="216" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">which would make it worthwhile for the prisoner to pursue. In the opinion of the Commission, </text>
<text top="229" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the State did not meet the burden of proof in this case and consequently the Commission finds </text>
<text top="241" left="57" width="108" height="12" font="2">this case admissible. </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>2. </b></text>
<text top="267" left="92" width="73" height="12" font="1"><b>Timely filing</b> </text>
<text top="293" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">18. The petition was presented within six months of the final ruling of the appeal on conviction </text>
<text top="305" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">and  sentence  pursuant  to  Article  46(1)(b)  of  the  Convention.  Mr.  Hilaire's  appeal  against </text>
<text top="318" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">conviction  and  sentence  was  dismissed  by  the  Court  of  Appeal  of  Trinidad  and  Tobago  on </text>
<text top="330" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">November  7,  1996.  His  application  for  leave  to  appeal  his  conviction  was  dismissed  by  the </text>
<text top="342" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Judicial Committee of the Privy Council in London, on November 6, 1997. The petition was filed </text>
<text top="354" left="57" width="225" height="12" font="2">before the Commission on October 7, 1997. </text>
<text top="380" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>3. </b></text>
<text top="380" left="92" width="275" height="12" font="1"><b>No duplication of other international procedures</b> </text>
<text top="406" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">19.  The  petition  satisfies  the  requirements  of  Article  46(1)(c)  in  that  it  is  not  pending </text>
<text top="418" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">settlement  in  another  international  proceeding,  nor  does  it  duplicate  a  petition  already </text>
<text top="431" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">examined  and  settled  by  the  Commission  or  by  another  international  governmental </text>
<text top="443" left="57" width="286" height="12" font="2">organization of which the State concerned is a member. </text>
<text top="469" left="57" width="20" height="12" font="1"><b>IV. </b></text>
<text top="469" left="92" width="79" height="12" font="1"><b>CONCLUSION</b> </text>
<text top="495" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">20. The Commission finds that the petition is admissible having satisfied the requirements of </text>
<text top="507" left="57" width="199" height="12" font="2">Article 46 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="533" left="57" width="272" height="12" font="2">21. Taking the foregoing considerations into account, </text>
<text top="560" left="136" width="327" height="12" font="1"><b>THE INTER-AMERICAN COMMISSION ON HUMAN RIGHTS, </b></text>
<text top="572" left="273" width="54" height="12" font="1"><b>DECIDES</b> </text>
<text top="598" left="57" width="216" height="12" font="2">1. To declare the present case admissible. </text>
<text top="624" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">2. To place itself at the disposal of the parties with a view to seeking a friendly settlement of </text>
<text top="636" left="57" width="477" height="12" font="2">the matter based on the respect for human rights, as recognized in the American Convention. </text>
<text top="662" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">3.  To  make  public  this  report  and  to  publish  it  in  its  Annual  Report  to  the  OAS  General </text>
<text top="675" left="57" width="55" height="12" font="2">Assembly. </text>
<text top="701" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Done and signed at the headquarters of the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights, in </text>
<text top="713" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">the  city  of  Washington,  D.C.,  on  the  25  day  of  the  month  of  September  in  the  year  1998. </text>
<text top="730" left="57" width="148" height="12" font="2">                                         </text>
<text top="742" left="57" width="3" height="6" font="7">2</text>
<text top="742" left="60" width="476" height="10" font="8"> In a Jamaican case, the U.N. Human Rights Committee held that &#34;in the absence of legal aid, a constitutional motion </text>
<text top="752" left="57" width="481" height="10" font="8">did not constitute an available remedy in the case.&#34; Communication No. 445/1991, Champagnie, Palmer and Chisholm </text>
<text top="762" left="57" width="431" height="10" font="8">v. Jamaica (views adopted on 18 July 1994, fifty-first session), U.N. Doc. CCPR/C/51/D/445/1191 (1994). </text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="9" size="12" family="AAAAAJ+TimesNewRomanPSMT" color="#000000"/>
<text top="801" left="296" width="6" height="8" font="0">5 </text>
<text top="57" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">(Signed): Carlos Ayala Corao, Chairman, Robert K. Goldman, First Vice Chairman; Jean Joseph </text>
<text top="69" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="2">Exume, Second  Vice  Chairman;  Commissioners  Alvaro  Tirado  Mejia,  Claudio  Grossman, Hélio </text>
<text top="81" left="57" width="125" height="12" font="2">Bicudo and Henry Forde.</text>
<text top="81" left="181" width="3" height="13" font="9"> </text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
