<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="23.08.0">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="0" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana,Bold" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana,Italic" color="#000000"/>
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">1 </text>
<text top="35" left="247" width="105" height="12" font="1"><b>REPORT Nº 95/06 </b></text>
<text top="48" left="257" width="85" height="12" font="0">PETITION 92-04 </text>
<text top="60" left="259" width="82" height="12" font="0">ADMISSIBILITY </text>
<text top="72" left="210" width="178" height="12" font="0">JESÚS TRANQUILINO VÉLEZ LOOR </text>
<text top="84" left="276" width="46" height="12" font="0">PANAMA </text>
<text top="96" left="253" width="92" height="12" font="0">October 23, 2006 </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="13" height="12" font="1"><b>I. </b></text>
<text top="121" left="85" width="61" height="12" font="1"><b>SUMMARY </b></text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">1.  On  February  10,  2004,  the  Inter-American  Commission  on  Human  Rights  (hereinafter </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">referred to as “IACHR”) received, by e-mail, a petition lodged by Jesús Tranquilino Vélez Loor </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">(hereinafter referred to as “the alleged victim”) in which he claims to have undergone torture, </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">forced  isolation,  and  mistreatment  at  the  hands  of  Panamanian  police  officers  at  two </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Panamanian detention centers without being given the opportunity to defend himself, without </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the  benefit  of  any  court  of  law,  without  being  allowed  to  make  a  telephone  call,  and  while </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">being  deprived  of  all  medical  care.  The  petition  alleges  violation  by  the  Panamanian  State </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">(hereinafter  known  as  “the  State”)  of  Articles  5  (Right  to  Humane  Treatment),  7  (Right  to </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Personal Liberty), 8 (Right to a Fair Trial), 10 (Right to Compensation), 21 (Right to Property), </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">and  25  (Right  to  Judicial  Protection)  of  the  American  Convention  on  Human  Rights  in </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">conjunction with Article 1.1, and Articles 1, 2, 3, 7, 8, 9, 10, and 11 of the Declaration on the </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Protection  of  All  Persons  from  Being  Subjected  to  Torture  and  Other  Cruel,  Inhuman,  or </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="369" height="12" font="0">Degrading Treatment or Punishment, to the detriment of Mr. Vélez Loor. </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">2.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor,  who  is  an  Ecuadorian  citizen,  states  that  the  Panamanian  border  police </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">arrested him on November 10, 2002 because he was not in possession of valid papers and did </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">not have the necessary visa. He was deported ten months later, on September 10, 2003. He </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">says that he was stripped of his possessions and that these were never  returned to him. He </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">also claims that he was kept in two different detention centers, and that he was mistreated in </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">both  in  a  variety  of  ways.  He  alleges  that  while  he  was  held in  detention he  was  sometimes </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">tortured and that he did not receive the medical care necessary to treat the consequences of </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the  torture  he  had  suffered.  He  adds  that  no  legal  investigation  into  the  torture  has  been </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">initiated  and  that  he  has  had  no  access  to  suitable  and  effective  legal  remedies  that  would </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="153" height="12" font="0">guarantee his right to justice. </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">3. The State informs that Mr. Vélez Loor was sentenced to a prison term for having repeatedly </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">entered  Panama  illegally.  Consequently,  the  State  emphasizes  that  his  arrest  was  legal  and </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">that  the  party  alleging  violation  of  his  rights  benefited  from  all  the  available  guarantees  to </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">safeguard his rights. The State points out that Panamanian law provides that foreign nationals, </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">who repeatedly enter Panama, without the necessary papers, will be imprisoned for two years </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">and  then  deported.  In  response  to  the  official  complaint  lodged  by  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  at  the </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Panamanian Embassy in Ecuador after he was deported, in which he claimed that he had been </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">mistreated  in  Panamanian  prisons,  the  State  emphasizes  that  the  Ministry  of  Foreign  Affairs </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">opened  an  investigation  of  the  complaint  both  with  the  National  Police  and  the  National </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Directorate  of  Immigration.  At  the  same  time,  it  rejects  Mr.  Vélez  Loor’s  allegations  with </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">regard to his purported lack of medical care and provides details regarding the six occasions on </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="301" height="12" font="0">which Mr. Vélez Loor was attended to by the prison doctor. </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="460" height="12" font="0">4.  After  analyzing  the  positions  of  the  parties,  the  Commission  concluded  that  it </text>
<text top="607" left="521" width="21" height="12" font="2"><i>has </i></text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="55" height="12" font="2"><i>jurisdiction</i></text>
<text top="619" left="112" width="430" height="12" font="0">  to  decide  on  the  complaint  made  by  the  petitioners  and  that  the  case  was </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">admissible,  under  Article  46  of  the  American  Convention.  The  Commission  has  decided  to </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">declare the case admissible under Articles 1.1, 2, 5, 8, 21, and 25 of the American Convention </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">as well as under Articles 1, 6, and 8 of the Inter-American Convention to Prevent and Punish </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Torture.  The  Commission  also  declares  inadmissible  the  alleged  violation  of  Article  10  of  the </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">American  Convention.  As  a  consequence,  the  Commission  will  serve  notice  of  its  decision  to </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="462" height="12" font="0">the parties concerned and will publish the present admissibility report in its Annual Report. </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="230" height="12" font="1"><b>II.  PROCESSING BY THE COMMISSION </b></text>
<text top="728" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">5.  The  original  petition  was  received  at  the  Commission  on  February  10,  2004  and  was </text>
<text top="753" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">registered as petition No. 92 of 2004. On August 3, 2004 the Commission received additional </text>
<text top="765" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">information  from  Mr.  Vélez  Loor.  On  March  17,  2005  Mr.  José  Villagrán  (hereinafter  “the </text>
<text top="777" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner”) was retained as Mr. Vélez Loor’s lawyer and presented arguments on April 12 and </text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="3" size="6" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">2 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">April 21 and again on June 14, 2005. On October 7, 2005 a hearing was requested before the </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Commission. In a letter dated November 7, 2005, Mr. Villagrán informed the Commission that </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">he was working on the case with the Permanent Committee for the Defense of Human Rights, </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">in Guayaquil, Ecuador. On December 21, 2005, the Commission communicated the petition to </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="0">the State in accordance with Article 30.3 of its Rules of Procedure and granted the State a two-</text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">month period within which to reply. On February 10, 2006 the State requested a one-month </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">extension  so  as  to  present  its  observations,  and  this  was  granted  until  March  6,  2006.  On </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">March  7,  2006  the  Commission  received  the  State’s  reply  and  this  was  transmitted  to  the </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioners on the same day. On March 9, 2006 the lawyer Walter Mendoza Yépez of the Legal </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Unit of the Permanent Committee on Human Rights in Ecuador (CDH), working in conjunction </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">with  the  petitioner,  Mr.  Villagrán,  requested  the  Commission  to  declare  that  Panama  had </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">violated  the  American  Convention  on  Human  Rights  and  the  Inter-American  Convention  to </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">Prevent and Punish Torture. On March 13, 2006 the Commission conducted a hearing on the </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="207" height="12" font="0">admissibility  of  the  case  during  its  124</text>
<text top="192" left="264" width="7" height="8" font="3">th</text>
<text top="194" left="271" width="271" height="12" font="0">  regular  session.  On  May  1,  2006  the  Commission </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">transmitted to the State the observations submitted by the petitioner on the State’s response </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="362" height="12" font="0">and the arguments put forward during the hearing held in March 2006. </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="20" height="12" font="1"><b>III.</b></text>
<text top="242" left="77" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="242" left="85" width="165" height="12" font="1"><b>POSITIONS OF THE PARTIES </b></text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="1"><b>A.</b></text>
<text top="267" left="68" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="267" left="85" width="83" height="12" font="1"><b>The Petitioner </b></text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">6. On November 10, 2002, Jesús Tranquilino Vélez Loor, a citizen of Ecuador, a merchant and </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">translator  by  profession,  declared  that  he  had  been  passing  through  Panama  when  he  was </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">arrested. Mr. Vélez Loor acknowledges that he did not have the required visa and that he was, </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">in  fact,  not  in  possession  of  valid  papers.  He  was  captured  by  border  police  in  the  town  of </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Nueva  Esperanza,  in  Darién  Province.  He  says  that  the  policemen  menaced  him  with  AK  47 </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">guns and demanded that he prostrate himself on the ground, threatening that they would kill </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">him,  while  they  searched  his  baggage,  in  which  he  was  carrying  US$1,900,  a  camera,  his </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">identity  card,  and  other  personal  effects.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  points  out  that  the  personal </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">possessions that he had with him at the time of his arrest were confiscated and never returned </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">to him. He states that he was handcuffed, his feet were shackled, and he was forced to walk </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">barefoot  to  a  small  military  barracks  in  a  small  indigenous  town  in  Embera.  There  he  was </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">handcuffed  to  a  metal  post  for  eight  hours  until  a  helicopter  belonging  to  the  former </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Panamanian Air Force moved him to the town of Meteti. There he was to remain for one week </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">in a small cell and was told that he would be held in custody for 3 or 4 years. From there he </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">was taken by boat to the Penitentiary located on La Palma Island, where more than 150 people </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="95" height="12" font="0">were in detention. </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">7.  According  to  Mr.  Vélez  Loor,  La  Palma  is  a  prison  for  extremely  dangerous  persons.  He </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">claims that he was kept with other prisoners who lived in fear of explosions as there was an </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">enormous petrol depot in the middle of the cellblock, which also had a suffocating effect on the </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">prisoners  at  night.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  states  that,  because  of  the  conditions  of  his  detention,  he </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">started a hunger strike with other people who had been imprisoned for lack of documentation, </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="242" height="12" font="0">demanding that they be deported immediately. </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">8.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  declares  that  following  his  protest,  he  was  savagely  tortured,  receiving  a </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">blow  to  his  spine  and  “a  fracture”  in  his  head  with  a  wooden  stick.  He  claims  that  he </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">recognized “Alirio” as one of the policeman who attacked him along with others who were not </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">wearing badges on their jackets. Mr. Vélez Loor indicates that Leoncio Ochoa, also Ecuadorian, </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">was  present  when  this  beating  occurred.  In  the  course  of  the  public  hearing  held  during  the </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="19" height="12" font="0">124</text>
<text top="642" left="76" width="7" height="8" font="3">th</text>
<text top="643" left="82" width="459" height="12" font="0"> regular session, Mr. Ochoa described to the Commission the manner in which the beating </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="82" height="12" font="0">was conducted: </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="680" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">Mr.  Ochoa  declared  that  it  was  the  jail-keeper  who  &#34;administered  a  heavy  blow  on  the </text>
<text top="692" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">head&#34;  to  Mr.  Vélez  Loor.  He  pointed  to  the  part  of  Vélez  Loor's  head  that  had  been </text>
<text top="704" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">struck. He indicates that on that same day no medical attention was given to Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="716" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">Loor. The rest of the prisoners tried to bind his head so as to help take care of him, but </text>
<text top="728" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">despite  their  efforts  on  his  behalf,  Mr.  Ochoa  emphasized  that  Vélez  was  in  extremely </text>
<text top="741" left="85" width="63" height="12" font="0">poor shape. </text>
<text top="753" left="85" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="765" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">The petitioner adds that Mr. Vélez Loor received no medical care, because at a hospital in </text>
<text top="777" left="85" width="250" height="12" font="0">La Palma he was told that he would have to pay. </text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">3 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">9.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  maintains  that  the  other  detainees  in  La  Palma  were  deported  by  boat  to </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Colombia, and that he was left alone with an injured back. On December 18, 2002, Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Loor was transferred by land to La Joyita prison, cellblock 6, in Panama City where he was to </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">stay for six months until June 1, 2003. After another hunger strike he was sent to maximum </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">security  block  12  where  he  was  to  endure  both  physical  and  psychological  torture  until </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="331" height="12" font="0">September 10, 2003, at which time he was deported to Ecuador. </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">10. Mr. Vélez has stated in his complaint that he was not allowed to communicate with either </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">his  family  or  with  the  Ecuadorian  Embassy.  He  further  asserts  that  it  was  only  thanks  to  a </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">telephone, kept illegally in the prison, that he was able to get in touch with the Consulate and </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="290" height="12" font="0">ask them to inform his family that he had been arrested. </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">11.  The  petitioner  alleges  that  in  La  Joyita  Prison,  in  February  2003,  in  poor  health  as  the </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">result of the terrible beatings he had endured at La Palma, he once again asked to be treated </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">by  a  doctor  —however,  this  request  was  denied.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  maintains  that  he  was  also </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">suffering from an ulcer and that the doctor who was treating him, whose name was José Aníbal </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Rodríguez Torres, prescribed for him some out-of-date medicine that made him vomit and that </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">produced intoxication. In March 2003 he fainted and was taken to Santo Tomás hospital and </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">there doctors informed him that he would have to pay USD $ 300 for the check-ups but since </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="215" height="12" font="0">he had no money, he would be left to die. </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">12.  The  petitioner  alleges  that  on  Sunday  June  1,  2003  the  victim  began  another  hunger </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">strike,  begged  for  medical  attention  and  sewed  his  mouth  shut.  As  a  reply,  a  police  officer </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="0">went to see him and told him that death would soon follow. He was  transferred to the high-</text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">security  punishment  block,  designed  for  extremely  dangerous  prisoners.  He  was  flung  into  a </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">damp and dark cell and told that they were going to unzip his lips with the benefit of gas and </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">truncheon. Then they stripped him naked, threw him to the ground, and started beating him </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">with  a  club  on  his  back,  his  legs,  and  his  feet.  Meanwhile  they  scraped  his  scalp  with  their </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">boots. He claims that while he was face downward, they lifted up his head and poured tear gas </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">in his face and eyes; he could not breathe and he had to force open the stitches in his mouth </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">in order to be able to breathe. He felt suffocated and unstitched his mouth and this produced </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">bleeding. They hit him on the soles of his feet while twisting the tendons of his legs. After this </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">lengthy torture, he recounts that Lieutenant P. locked him up, still naked, in a small cell known </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">as  “the  discotheque”  in  block  12  of  La  Joyita,  where  they  used  the  “rotura  blanca”  (&#34;clean </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">break&#34; method) which would not leave any traces. There they poured tear gas powder on his </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">body and around the cell; the prisoners who have undergone this punishment refer to this dust </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">as anthrax on account of the terrible suffocation that it produces. Then a member of the guard </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">proposed that he submit to oral sex if he wanted to buy his way out of the Discotheque. The </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner  said  that  he  refused  this  offer  and,  as  a  result,  the  guard  took  out  white  powder </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">from his bag and threw it on his back, smeared it on a pencil and inserted it into his rectum. </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="418" height="12" font="0">According to the petition, this burnt like fire and turned his whole body bright red. </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">13. Mr. Vélez Loor alleges that after a few hours they took him out of the Discotheque and put </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">him  into  a  dark,  cold,  and  damp  cell  where  four  extremely  dangerous  prisoners  were  being </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">kept. But nobody asked him anything as he was at death's door with his mouth half stitched </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">up. He lay down on a piece of newspaper and ran a high fever. After 17 days of the hunger </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">strike,  he  started  drinking  a  cup  of  tea  every  morning  but  he  maintains  that  his  health  was </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">shattered. On July 27, 2003 a fellow prisoner paid some money so that a guard could arrange </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">a medical appointment for him and it was during this consultation that the doctor detected an </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="417" height="12" font="0">ulcer. The report on his situation was sent to the Ecuadorian Embassy in Panama. </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">14.  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  adds  that  despite  the  gravity  of  his  condition  and  the  lack  of  specialized </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">medical  care,  the  doctors  sent  misleading  reports  to  the  Ecuadorian  Embassy  in  which  they </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">stated that they were in fact treating him. During the period of his detention, he had no access </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">to a lawyer, was not aware of the charges that were being brought against him, and he had no </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="339" height="12" font="0">knowledge of the judicial authority that had ordered his detention. </text>
<text top="728" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="4" size="12" family="Times New Roman" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="8" family="ABCDEE+Verdana" color="#000000"/>
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">4 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">15. In the original complaint, he stated that he lacked sufficient evidence of the torture he had </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="410" height="12" font="0">received because any document that implicated the police officers was forbidden.</text>
<text top="47" left="467" width="4" height="8" font="3">1</text>
<text top="48" left="471" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">16. In a number of communications, the petitioner gave information about  the steady decline </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">of his health due to the consequences, both physical and psychological, of the torture he had </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">received.  The  Commission  was  told  that  the  alleged  victim  did  not  have  the  support  of  the </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Ecuadorian State, that he did not have the financial wherewithal for medical treatment, that he </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="373" height="12" font="0">was not well enough to perform many tasks, and that his life was at risk. </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">17.  With  regard  to  the  State’s  arguments  about  the  nonexistence  of  the  criminal  complaint </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">presented  by  the  petitioner  with  regard  to  the  alleged  torture  that  he  had  suffered,  the </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner points out that after filing the complaint with the Panamanian Embassy in Ecuador, </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">subsequent to September 10, 2003, the Panamanian State should have initiated the pertinent </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">criminal  proceedings  in  order  to  investigate  the  facts  of  the  case.  He  adds  that  the  State </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">cannot divest itself of the burden of proof with respect to the initiation of criminal proceedings. </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">The  petitioner  points  out  that  the  sole  remedy  available  to  him  once  he  was  outside  of </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Panamanian territory,  was to approach the  Embassy of Panama. He alleges that the State  is </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">willing  to  move  forward  with  investigations  only  now  that  the  case  has  been  denounced </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="42" height="12" font="0">abroad. </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">18. Moreover, Mr. Vélez Loor points out that he was not informed as to his rights at the time </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">he  was  arrested.  He  adds  that  the  Panamanian  government  never  notified  the  Ecuadorian </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Consular Mission of his arrest, so that his expatriation might be processed. He states that the </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">imposition  of  a  prison  term  was  done  without  considering  the  possibility  of  allowing  him  to </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">defend  himself  and  that  no  judge  tried  his  case.  Specifically,  the  petitioner  highlights  the </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="475" height="12" font="0">statement made by the Minister of Justice in the course of the public hearing held in the 124</text>
<text top="338" left="532" width="7" height="8" font="3">th</text>
<text top="339" left="539" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">regular  session,  to  the  effect  that  no  judicial  authority is  informed  during  the  proceedings  in </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">which a prison sentence is imposed on repeat-offender illegal immigrants. The petitioner points </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">out that he was not given a public defender and he was not allowed access to a private lawyer, </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">given  that  he  had  been  forcibly  prevented  from  making  any  contact  with  the  outside  world. </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Moreover,  he  points  out,  it  is  unlikely  that  a  private  lawyer  would  want  to  defend  an </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">immigrant,  without  papers,  and  with  no  money  to  guarantee  payment  of  his  fees.  The </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner  states  that  the  administrative  process  involved  in  putting  an  undocumented </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">immigrant on trial makes no provision for possible defense and that the person who orders the </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="228" height="12" font="0">imprisonment is an administrative authority. </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">19. The petitioner alleges that as a consequence of the actions taken against him that Panama </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">is  responsible  internationally  for  the  violation  of  articles  5  (personal  integrity),  7  (personal </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">liberty), 8 (due process), 10 (indemnization), 21 (right to property) and 25 (access to justice) </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="147" height="12" font="0">of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="1"><b>B.</b></text>
<text top="534" left="68" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="534" left="85" width="57" height="12" font="1"><b>The State </b></text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">20.  In its response, dated March 6, 2006, the  State introduced its argument by pointing out </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">that Mr. Vélez Loor had entered Panama illegally on a number of previous occasions. The State </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">notes that on September 16, 1996, Mr. Vélez Loor was arrested by Units of the National Police </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">and sent to the National Directorate for Migration and Naturalization (hereinafter referred to as </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">“the  Directorate  of  Migration”)  for  having  entered  Panamanian  territory  through  Darién </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Province, without any documents to accredit his identity or nationality. In light of the above, </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">on September 18, 1996, Mr. Vélez Loor was deported for having entered the country illegally, </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">pursuant to resolution No. 6425 of September 18, 1996. This resolution stated that Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Loor would be unable to enter Panama again without the express agreement of the Directorate </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">of Migration. Moreover, this resolution informed Mr. Vélez of the content of Article 67 of Decree </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="153" height="12" font="0">Law No. 16 of June 30, 1960: </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="704" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">Article 67. Foreigners sentenced to deportation who evade this sentence by staying in the </text>
<text top="716" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">country in a clandestine way or who flout the decision by returning will be forced to carry </text>
<text top="735" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="746" left="57" width="485" height="10" font="5">1 In the original complaint, received on February 10, 2004, the petitioner identified some policemen who had allegedly </text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="484" height="10" font="5">participated in his torture during his detention at La Palma prison (Darién Province). He refers to a policeman called </text>
<text top="765" left="57" width="484" height="10" font="5">“Arturo”, a policeman who had the nickname “Músculo”. During the time he was held at La Joyita prison, he refers to </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="484" height="10" font="5">Mike  Castillo  and  “Lieutenant  Wallker”  [sic],  Lieut.  Patiño,  Adalides  Batista,  Corporal  (“Cabo”)  García,  Police  Officer </text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="369" height="10" font="5">Camargo and “others that cannot be identified because they tried to conceal their names.” </text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">5 </text>
<text top="35" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">out agricultural tasks in the Coiba Penal Colony for two (2) years and forced to leave the </text>
<text top="48" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">country after this period has finished; they may be released if they submit travel tickets </text>
<text top="60" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">for  leaving  the  country  in  a  manner  satisfactory  to  the  Ministry  of  the  Interior  and </text>
<text top="72" left="85" width="41" height="12" font="0">Justice. </text>
<text top="84" left="85" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">21. The State points out that  despite the above warning, Mr. Vélez Loor was arrested by the </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">National  Police  on  January  3,  2002  near  the  town  of  Tupiza,  Darién  Province,  close  to  the </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">border  with  Colombia.  The  reason  for  his  arrest  was  the  fact  that  he  “did  not  have  any </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">document which justified or authorized his physical presence on national territory”. Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">was  handed  over  to  the  Migration  authorities  and  subsequently  deported  pursuant  to </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="407" height="12" font="0">Resolution No. 0185 of January 9, 2002, leaving the country for Quito, Ecuador. </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">22. The State points out that on September 11, 2002, the Police of Darién arrested Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Loor  for  a  third  time,  after  he  circumvented  immigration  controls  by  entering  once  again </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">through Tupiza, Nueva Esperanza, Darién Province, near the border with Colombia. The State </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">wishes to note that, upon his arrest, Mr. Vélez Loor was carrying no documentation authorizing </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">his  presence  in  Panama,  nor  was  he  carrying  any  document  to  accredit  his  identity  and </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">nationality,  nor  was  he  in  possession  of  valuables  of  any  kind.  On  November  12,  2002,  Mr. </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="452" height="12" font="0">Vélez  was  placed  at  the  disposal  of  the  Directorate  of  Migration  and  Naturalization,</text>
<text top="253" left="510" width="4" height="8" font="3">2</text>
<text top="254" left="514" width="29" height="12" font="0">  and </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">registered  on  the  same  day.  The  State  alludes  to  the  fact  that  in  this  register,  the  detainee </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="46" height="12" font="0">declared </text>
<text top="279" left="104" width="45" height="12" font="2"><i>inter alia</i></text>
<text top="279" left="149" width="393" height="12" font="0"> that his objective had been “to reach Mexico because his grandfather lives </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">there  and  he  had,  a  few  days  previously,  been  arrested  by  the  FARC  [Revolutionary  Armed </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Forces of Colombia] and was afraid that this might happen again”. The State points out that </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="227" height="12" font="0">the  prisoner's  background  information  file  (</text>
<text top="315" left="284" width="107" height="12" font="2"><i>diligencia  de  filiación</i></text>
<text top="315" left="392" width="150" height="12" font="0">)  made  no  reference  to  any </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="233" height="12" font="0">personal possessions of value to be recorded. </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">23.  The  State  notes  that  on  November  12,  2002,  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  was  transferred  to  the  La </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="0">Palma Public Prison in Darién. Once there, he was kept, for one month, in a cellblock for well-</text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="159" height="12" font="0">behaved and elderly prisoners. </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">24. On December 6, 2002, the Directorate of Migration and Naturalization issued Resolution No </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">7306, in which it applied the aforementioned Article 67 of Decree Law 16 of 1960 to Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Loor. It sentenced him to two years' imprisonment, given that Mr. Vélez had been deported on </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">two previous occasions and that he had previously been forbidden to re-enter the country. An </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">order was then issued for him to be transferred to the La Joyita Penitentiary. On December 11, </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">2002,  the  Penitentiary  System  Directorate  recorded  the  fact  that  Mr.  Vélez  had  entered  the </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="307" height="12" font="0">system and he was duly transferred on December 19, 2002. </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">25.  The  State  points  out  that,  once  the  necessary  formalities  for  repatriation  had  been </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">complied  with,  on  September  8,  2003  the  Directorate  of  Migration  and  Naturalization  issued </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Resolution No. 8230 on September 8, 2003, in which it invalidated the resolution of December </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">6, 2002. As a result, the departure of Mr. Vélez Loor was ordered and he was transferred on </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">September  9,  2003  to  the  facilities  of  the  Directorate  of  Migration  and  Naturalization  of  the </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Ministry of the Interior and Justice with a view to his subsequent deportation. On September </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">10,  2003,  he  traveled  to  his  native  country,  Ecuador,  on  Avianca  Airlines  flight  061  at  6:40 </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="23" height="12" font="0">pm. </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">26. The State reports that, once he was in Ecuador, Mr. Vélez Loor made a formal complaint to </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the  Panamanian  Embassy  in  Ecuador,  regarding  the  physical  mistreatment  that  he  had  been </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">allegedly subjected to within the Panamanian prison system. The State explains that this led to </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">an  investigation  of  the  facts,  as  of  January  27,  2004,  carried  out  by  the  Ministry  of  Foreign </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Affairs.  The  National  Police  and  the  Directorate  of  Migration  and  Naturalization  sent  reports </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">relating to the legality of the detention. This information was sent to the Panamanian Embassy </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="280" height="12" font="0">in Quito on April 13, 2004, for forwarding to Mr. Vélez. </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">27.  On  September  15,  2004,  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  once  again  complained  about  the  alleged </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">mistreatment he had  received and he submitted a new complaint relating to the payment  of </text>
<text top="728" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">2500.00  balboas  for  the  issuance  of  a  tourist  visa,  allegedly  issued  by  the  Panamanian </text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Consulate  in  Cartagena  de  Indias,  Colombia.  In  this  regard,  on  September  27,  2004,  the </text>
<text top="774" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="254" height="10" font="5">2 Official Letter No. ZPD/SDIIP 92-02, of November 12, 2002. </text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="6" size="10" family="ABCDEE+Verdana,BoldItalic" color="#000000"/>
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">6 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="477" height="12" font="0">Foreign  Policy  Directorate  of  the  Ministry  of  Foreign  Affairs  sent  a  reply  to  Mr.  Vélez  Loor,</text>
<text top="34" left="535" width="4" height="8" font="3">3</text>
<text top="35" left="539" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">asking  him  to  provide  proof  of  the  payment  that  he  had  made.  The  State  indicated  that  it </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">made this request because there was no evidence in the Directorate of Migration archives that </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">payment in that amount had been made for a visa. The State says that it never received any </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="214" height="12" font="0">reply to its request regarding this matter. </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">28. With regard to the complaints relating to physical mistreatment, the State points out that </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">during his imprisonment, Mr. Vélez Loor was treated by the prison doctor on six occasions. The </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">State notes that on April 10, 2003, Mr. Vélez was summoned for a medical evaluation but that </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">he  refused  to  go.  On  April  22,  2003,  he  was  evaluated  for  headaches  and  dizziness,  the </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">product of a former cranial fracture, and a CAT scan of the brain was prescribed. On June 2, </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">2003,  Mr.  Vélez  said  he  was  on  a  hunger  strike  and  said  that  he  would  not  be  taking  any </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">medicine. The State points out that on June 11, 2003, Mr. Vélez was attended to on account of </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">his having been on a hunger strike for eleven days, with half of his lips stitched together. At </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">this  point  he  was  alleging  that  he  had  not  been  attended  to  and  that  he  was  suffering  from </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">gastritis,  which  had  been  diagnosed  as  a  consequence  of  his  refusal  to  take  any  food,  and </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">medical treatment was ordered. On June 12, 2003 Mr. Vélez was taken by security personnel </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">to  the  Clinic  but  he  denied  that  he  required  medical  attention  and  said that  he  would  refuse </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">any medicine. According to the State, on June 27, 2003, Mr. Vélez was once again examined </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">by the doctor, who reached the conclusion that the detainee had light-to-moderate anemia and </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">clinical signs of likely gastritis. The State adds that at one point Mr. Vélez was moved to the </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="376" height="12" font="0">clinic at the La Joya prison to receive medical care for a common ailment. </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">29. According to the State, the Directorate of the Penitentiary System pointed out that in the </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">medical check-ups that had been carried out, there was no evidence of physical abuse, nor did </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="418" height="12" font="0">the prison report suggest that Mr. Vélez had been the victim of the alleged abuse. </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">30. In wrapping up the statement in its defense, the State argues that given that the focus of </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the  investigation  thus  far  has  been  of  an  administrative  nature,  no  criminal  investigation </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">strictly  speaking  has  been  set  in  motion,  “inasmuch  as  the  petitioner  has  filed  no  formal </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">application with the domestic judicial authorities having jurisdiction to order the performance </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">of  the  necessary  inquiries  in  response  to  the  allegations  that  have  been  made,  to  clarify  the </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">facts  of  the  case,  and  to  try  and  prosecute  those  responsible.”  The  State  calls  upon  the </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Commission to kindly lend “its assistance so that a request can be made to the petitioner to </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">provide  all  additional  evidence  and  information  to  enable  the  national  government  to  initiate </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">appropriate criminal investigations warranted by the case at hand, in order to clarify the facts </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">described  by  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  in  his  petition  and  thereby  ensure,  through  the  domestic </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">jurisdiction of the Panamanian Government, that those responsible for perpetrating the alleged </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">crimes  may  be  brought  to  justice.”  Finally,  the  State  requests  that  the  petition  be  deemed </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="260" height="12" font="0">inadmissible and that the case in question be filed. </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="378" height="12" font="1"><b>IV.  ANALYSIS CONCERNING JURISDICTION AND ADMISSIBILITY </b></text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="1"><b>A.</b></text>
<text top="558" left="68" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="558" left="85" width="69" height="12" font="1"><b>Jurisdiction </b></text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="1"><b>1.</b></text>
<text top="583" left="67" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="583" left="85" width="173" height="12" font="1"><b>The Commission's jurisdiction </b></text>
<text top="583" left="259" width="103" height="12" font="6"><i><b>rationae personae</b></i></text>
<text top="583" left="361" width="7" height="12" font="1"><b>, </b></text>
<text top="583" left="369" width="64" height="12" font="6"><i><b>ratione loci</b></i></text>
<text top="583" left="433" width="7" height="12" font="1"><b>, </b></text>
<text top="583" left="441" width="94" height="12" font="6"><i><b>ratione temporis</b></i></text>
<text top="583" left="535" width="7" height="12" font="1"><b>, </b></text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="24" height="12" font="1"><b>and </b></text>
<text top="595" left="81" width="97" height="12" font="6"><i><b>ratione materiae </b></i></text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">31.  The  petitioner  is  entitled  under  Article  44  of  the  American  Convention  to  lodge  petitions </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">with the Commission. The petition names Jesus Velez Loor as the alleged victim, whose rights </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">under  the  American  Convention  Panama  has  pledged  to  respect  and  guarantee.  As  for  the </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">State, the Commission points out that Panama signed the American Convention on November </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">22,  1969  and  ratified  it  on  June  22,  1978.  Additionally,  Panama  ratified  the  Inter-American </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Convention to Prevent and Punish Torture on August 28, 1991. Therefore, the Commission has </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="59" height="12" font="0">jurisdiction </text>
<text top="692" left="115" width="91" height="12" font="2"><i>rationae personae</i></text>
<text top="692" left="206" width="128" height="12" font="0"> to examine the petition. </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="186" height="12" font="0">32. The Commission has jurisdiction </text>
<text top="716" left="243" width="55" height="12" font="2"><i>ratione loci</i></text>
<text top="716" left="299" width="243" height="12" font="0"> because the alleged violations are said to have </text>
<text top="728" left="57" width="390" height="12" font="0">taken place within the territory of a State party to the American Convention. </text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="774" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="207" height="10" font="5">3 Note DGPE-CC-2866-04 of September 27, 2004. </text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
	<fontspec id="7" size="8" family="ABCDEE+Verdana,Italic" color="#000000"/>
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">7 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="251" height="12" font="0">33. With regard to the Commission's jurisdiction </text>
<text top="35" left="308" width="83" height="12" font="2"><i>ratione temporis</i></text>
<text top="35" left="391" width="151" height="12" font="0"> to examine the petition, the </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">facts are said to have occurred as of November 2002, by which time the international human </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="378" height="12" font="0">rights instruments applicable to the case were already in force in Panama. </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="221" height="12" font="0">34.  Finally,  the  Commission  is  competent </text>
<text top="84" left="279" width="89" height="12" font="2"><i>ratione  materiae,</i></text>
<text top="84" left="368" width="174" height="12" font="0">  because  the  petition  denounces </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">violations  of  human  rights  protected  by  the  American  Convention  and  by  the  Inter-American </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="218" height="12" font="0">Convention to Prevent and Punish Torture. </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="11" height="12" font="1"><b>2.</b></text>
<text top="133" left="67" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="133" left="85" width="190" height="12" font="1"><b>Exhaustion of domestic remedies </b></text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">35.  Article  46.1.a  of  the  American  Convention  states  that  admission by  the  Commission  of a </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petition  or  communication  lodged  in  accordance  with  Article  44  shall  be  subject  to  the </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">requirement  that  the  remedies  under  domestic  law  have  been  pursued  and  exhausted  in </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">accordance  with  generally  recognized  principles  of  international  law.  The  purpose  of  this </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">requirement is to allow national authorities to learn of the alleged violation of a protected right </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="454" height="12" font="0">and, in appropriate cases, to resolve it before it is taken before an international instance. </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">36.  The  requirement  of  prior  exhaustion  of  remedies  is  met  when  the  national  system  is </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">furnished with remedies that are adequate and effective to repair the alleged violation. In this </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">connection,  the  exception  to  the  requirement  to  exhaust  domestic  remedies,  contained  in </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Article  46.2  of  the  American  Convention,  does  not  apply  when  there  is  denial  of  justice:  the </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">domestic  legislation  of  the  State  concerned  does  not  afford  due  process  of  law  for  the </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">protection of the right or rights that have allegedly been violated; the party alleging violation </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">of  his  rights  has  been  denied  access  to  the  remedies  under  domestic  law  or  has  been </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">prevented  from  exhausting  them;  or  there  has  been  unwarranted  delay  in  rendering  a  final </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">judgment under the aforementioned remedies. As indicated by Article 31 of the Commission’s </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Rules of Procedure, when the petitioner contends that he or she is unable to prove compliance </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">with  the  requirement  indicated  in  this  article,  it  shall  be  up  to  the  State  concerned  to </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">demonstrate  to  the  Commission  that  the  remedies  under  domestic  law  have  not  been </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="347" height="12" font="0">previously exhausted, unless that is clearly evident from the record. </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">37.  Based  on  inferences  from  the  principles  of  international  law,  as  reflected  in  precedents </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">established by the Commission and the Inter-American Court of Human Rights, it is especially </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="0">important that the State against which a claim is being lodged should invoke the plea of non-</text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">exhaustion  of  domestic  remedies  in  the  early  stages  of  the  proceedings  before  the </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="64" height="12" font="0">Commission.</text>
<text top="460" left="121" width="4" height="8" font="3">4</text>
<text top="461" left="125" width="417" height="12" font="0"> At the same time, given the burden of proof incumbent upon it in such matters, </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the State that alleges non-exhaustion should point to the domestic remedies that need to be </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="240" height="12" font="0">exhausted and give proof of their effectiveness.</text>
<text top="484" left="297" width="4" height="8" font="3">5</text>
<text top="485" left="301" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">38. In the instant case, the petitioner first invoked the exception established in Article 46.2 of </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the  American  Convention,  whereby  the  party  alleging  violation  of  his  rights,  Mr.  Vélez  Loor, </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">was  not  allowed  access  to  domestic  remedies,  in  light  of  his  deportee  status.  His  second </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">argument  in  support  of  applying  the  exception  to  the  requirement  to  exhaust  domestic </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">remedies is the fact that the alleged victim was unable to pay a lawyer to take the case to the </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Panamanian  courts,  pursuant  to  Advisory  Opinion  11/90  of  the  Inter-American  Court.  The </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner explains that it was impossible for Mr. Vélez Loor to have access to remedies under </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">domestic law  as  he  had  no  fixed  employment,  given  that  he is  a  person  who  makes  a  living </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="292" height="12" font="0">from selling miscellaneous articles, such as markers, etc. </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">39.  Also  attached  are  a  number  of  complaints  made  by  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  before  the  Human </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Rights  Commission  of  the  National  Congress  of  Ecuador,  the  Office  of  the  Ombudsperson  of </text>
<text top="667" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="678" left="57" width="71" height="10" font="5">4 I/A Court H.R., </text>
<text top="678" left="128" width="308" height="10" font="7"><i>The Mayagna (Sumo) Awas Tingni Community Case, Preliminary Objections.</i></text>
<text top="678" left="436" width="105" height="10" font="5"> Judgment of February 1, </text>
<text top="688" left="57" width="132" height="10" font="5">2000, para. 53; I/A Court H.R., </text>
<text top="688" left="189" width="187" height="10" font="7"><i>Castillo Petruzzi Case, Preliminary Objections.</i></text>
<text top="688" left="376" width="165" height="10" font="5"> Judgment of September 4, 1998, para. </text>
<text top="697" left="57" width="86" height="10" font="5">56;  I/A  Court  H.R., </text>
<text top="697" left="145" width="192" height="10" font="7"><i>Loayza  Tamayo  Case,  Preliminary  Objections.</i></text>
<text top="697" left="337" width="205" height="10" font="5">  Judgment  of  January  31,  1996,  para.  40.  The </text>
<text top="707" left="57" width="484" height="10" font="5">Commission  and  the  Court  have  found  that  the  early  stages  of  the  proceedings  should  be  defined  as  the  stage  for </text>
<text top="717" left="57" width="464" height="10" font="5">assessing the admissibility of the proceedings before the Commission —i.e., before any assessment of the merits. </text>
<text top="717" left="521" width="21" height="10" font="7"><i>See, </i></text>
<text top="726" left="57" width="49" height="10" font="7"><i>for example</i></text>
<text top="726" left="105" width="216" height="10" font="5">, IACHR, Report No. 71/05, P-543/04, Admissibility, </text>
<text top="726" left="321" width="136" height="10" font="7"><i>Ever de [Jesús] Montero Mindiola</i></text>
<text top="726" left="458" width="84" height="10" font="5">, Colombia, October </text>
<text top="736" left="57" width="155" height="10" font="5">13, 2005, which cites, I/A Court H.R., </text>
<text top="736" left="212" width="81" height="10" font="7"><i>Herrera Ulloa Case. </i></text>
<text top="736" left="293" width="148" height="10" font="5">Judgment of July 2, 2004, para. 81. </text>
<text top="746" left="57" width="8" height="10" font="5">5 </text>
<text top="746" left="67" width="11" height="10" font="7"><i>Cf.</i></text>
<text top="746" left="79" width="222" height="10" font="5">  IACHR,  Report  Nº  32/05,  P-642/03,  Admissibility, </text>
<text top="746" left="303" width="239" height="10" font="7"><i>Luis  Rolando  Cuscul  Pivaral  et  al.  (persons  living  with </i></text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="43" height="10" font="7"><i>HIV/AIDS)</i></text>
<text top="756" left="99" width="248" height="10" font="5">, Guatemala, March 7, 2005, paras. 33-35; I/A Court H.R., </text>
<text top="756" left="348" width="194" height="10" font="7"><i>The Mayagna (Sumo) Awas Tingni Community </i></text>
<text top="765" left="57" width="121" height="10" font="7"><i>Case,  Preliminary  Objections,</i></text>
<text top="765" left="178" width="135" height="10" font="5">  Judgment  of  February  1,  2000,</text>
<text top="765" left="313" width="27" height="10" font="7"><i>  supra</i></text>
<text top="765" left="339" width="147" height="10" font="5">,  note  4,  para.  53;  I/A  Court  H.R.,</text>
<text top="765" left="486" width="55" height="10" font="7"><i>  Durand  and </i></text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="154" height="10" font="7"><i>Ugarte  Case,  Preliminary  Objections,</i></text>
<text top="775" left="211" width="170" height="10" font="5">  Judgment  of  May  28,  1999,  para.  33; </text>
<text top="775" left="382" width="159" height="10" font="7"><i>Cantoral  Benavides  Case,  Preliminary </i></text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="45" height="10" font="7"><i>Objections,</i></text>
<text top="785" left="102" width="179" height="10" font="5"> Judgment of September 3, 1998, para. 31. </text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">8 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Ecuador, and the Panamanian Embassy in Ecuador. Dated September 16, 2003, six days after </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">his  deportation,  the  Executive  Director  of  the  Ecumenical  Commission  of  Human  Rights </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">(CEDHU) sent a letter to the Consul General of the Republic of Ecuador in Panama, asking for </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">his  help  in  recovering  the  passport,  identity  card,  military  passbook  and  medical  certificates </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">belonging  to  Mr.  Vélez  Loor.  At  the  same  time,  a  complaint  about  the  torture  that  had  been </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">administered during his period in detention and the confiscation of his possessions was faxed </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">to  the  Panamanian  Embassy  in  Ecuador  on  February  2004.  According  to  the  petitioner,  the </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="430" height="12" font="0">complaint led to an investigation which concluded that the detention had been legal. </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>a. </b></text>
<text top="145" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="1"><b>It is alleged that the party alleging violation of his rights was denied access to </b></text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="282" height="12" font="1"><b>domestic remedies, in light of his deportee status </b></text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">40.  In  previous  cases,  the  Commission  has  declared  admissible  petitions  of  individuals  who </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">were deported and not permitted to re-enter the State which allegedly violated their rights, to </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="440" height="12" font="0">enable  them  to  challenge  the  human  rights  violations  they  have  allegedly  endured.</text>
<text top="205" left="497" width="4" height="8" font="3">6</text>
<text top="206" left="501" width="41" height="12" font="0">  In  the </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="86" height="12" font="2"><i>Chamorro Quiroz</i></text>
<text top="218" left="142" width="186" height="12" font="0"> case, petitioners argued as follows: </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="242" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">… that Mr. Chamorro was not “materially” able to invoke domestic legal remedies before </text>
<text top="254" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">leaving  the  country  because  he  was  taken  directly  from  where  he  was  captured  to  the </text>
<text top="267" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">place  where  he  was  deported.  According  to  the  petitioners,  detaining  undocumented </text>
<text top="279" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">immigrants for several hours before deporting them is an administrative measure, taken </text>
<text top="291" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">within  highly  summary,  almost  automatic,  proceedings,  that  does  not  allow  them  the </text>
<text top="303" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">opportunity  of  filing  or  attempting  to  seek  any  domestic  remedy,  including  habeas </text>
<text top="315" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">corpus. In addition, since they had no papers and no means of economic support, they </text>
<text top="327" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">were unable to reenter Costa Rica to formulate complaints or invoke the applicable legal </text>
<text top="339" left="85" width="176" height="12" font="0">remedies, as claimed by the State.</text>
<text top="338" left="261" width="4" height="8" font="3">7</text>
<text top="339" left="265" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="35" height="12" font="0">41.  In </text>
<text top="364" left="93" width="87" height="12" font="2"><i>Chamorro Quiroz</i></text>
<text top="364" left="180" width="362" height="12" font="0">, the  IACHR decided to allow the petition on account  of the  fact that </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">this  was  a  clear  case  of  the  circumstances  referred  to  in  Article  46(2)(b)  of  the  American </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="438" height="12" font="0">Convention which states that Article 46(1)(a) and 46(1)(b) shall not be applied when: </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="412" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="0">the  party  alleging  violation  of  his  rights  has  been  denied  access  to  the  remedies  under </text>
<text top="424" left="85" width="305" height="12" font="0">domestic law or has been prevented from exhausting them. </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="89" height="12" font="0">The  facts  of  the </text>
<text top="449" left="148" width="88" height="12" font="2"><i>Chamorro  Quiroz</i></text>
<text top="449" left="236" width="306" height="12" font="0">  case  demonstrated  to  the  Commission  that,  despite  the </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">official position expressed by the State, to the effect that deported foreigners had access to the </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="160" height="12" font="0">legal  remedies  of  annulment  (</text>
<text top="473" left="217" width="56" height="12" font="2"><i>revocatoria</i></text>
<text top="473" left="273" width="78" height="12" font="0">)  and  appeal  (</text>
<text top="473" left="351" width="47" height="12" font="2"><i>apelación</i></text>
<text top="473" left="398" width="144" height="12" font="0">)  proceedings,  it  was  later </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">proven  that  in  actual  fact  they  were  not  in  possession  of  these  rights.  The  Law  concerning </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Migration and Aliens, according to the manner in which the State of Costa Rica interpreted its </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">own laws, was interpreted to mean that undocumented aliens, on account of the fact that their </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">situation was &#34;absolutely illegal&#34; (in other words, because they had entered the State’s territory </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="411" height="12" font="0">without proper authorization, without immigration papers), enjoyed no such rights.</text>
<text top="533" left="468" width="4" height="8" font="3">8</text>
<text top="534" left="472" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">42.  Mr.  Chamorro  lacked  an  opportunity  to  invoke  domestic  legal  remedies  prior  to  leaving </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Costa Rica because he  was driven directly from the place he was captured to the place from </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">which he was deported. Comparing the case of Mr. Vélez Loor with that of Mr. Chamorro, Mr. </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Vélez also lacked the opportunity of invoking domestic remedies before leaving the country as </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">he  was  driven  to  a  detention  center  where  he  was  not  allowed  any  contact  with  the  outside </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">world.  He  alleges  that  he  was  not  allowed  to  use  the  telephone  or  have  any  contact  with </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">consular agents from Ecuador. He furthermore asserts that he was only allowed access to one </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">lawyer  who  was  unable  to  visit  him  in  person.  Consequently,  irrespective  of  whether  the </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">administrative or legal remedies could have been available to him, for practical purposes such </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="163" height="12" font="0">remedies were out of his reach. </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="486" height="12" font="0">43. The Commission finds that with regard to the first argument presented by the petitioner, </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the State did not allow Mr. Vélez Loor access to remedies under domestic law to challenge the </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">alleged arbitrary detention and the mistreatment and torture that he purportedly suffered. The </text>
<text top="735" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="746" left="57" width="242" height="10" font="5">6 See IACHR, Admissibility Report Nº 37/01, Case 11.529, </text>
<text top="746" left="298" width="149" height="10" font="7"><i>José Sánchez Guner Espinales et al. </i></text>
<text top="746" left="447" width="94" height="10" font="5">(Costa Rica), February </text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="293" height="10" font="5">22,  2001,  and  IACHR,  Admissibility  Report  Nº  89/00,  Case  11.495, </text>
<text top="756" left="352" width="127" height="10" font="7"><i>Juan  Ramón  Chamorro  Quiroz</i></text>
<text top="756" left="479" width="62" height="10" font="5">  (Costa  Rica), </text>
<text top="765" left="57" width="71" height="10" font="5">October 5, 2000. </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="8" height="10" font="5">7 </text>
<text top="775" left="65" width="16" height="10" font="7"><i>Ibid</i></text>
<text top="775" left="80" width="171" height="10" font="5">. Admissibility Report Nº 89/00, para. 35. </text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="8" height="10" font="5">8 </text>
<text top="785" left="65" width="16" height="10" font="7"><i>Ibid</i></text>
<text top="785" left="80" width="48" height="10" font="5">., para. 34. </text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="294" width="10" height="12" font="0">9 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Commission  concludes  that  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  was  prevented  from  exhausting  these  remedies </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">because he was arrested and then forbidden to use the telephone or have any other contact </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">with  the  world  outside  his  prison.  Consequently,  the  requirement  of  exhaustion  of  remedies </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">under  domestic  law  is  not  applicable  to  the  petitioner  in  accordance  with  the  exception </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="284" height="12" font="0">enshrined in Article 46.2.b of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>b. </b></text>
<text top="108" left="85" width="457" height="12" font="1"><b>The petitioner is asserting that he lacked the means to pay for a lawyer to take </b></text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="200" height="12" font="1"><b>his case before Panamanian courts </b></text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">44. The petitioner also  adduces the extreme  state of hardship in which Mr. Vélez Loor  found </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">himself  as  justification  for  not  being  required  to  exhaust  domestic  remedies  in  Panama  in </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="417" height="12" font="0">addition to invoking the impossibility of gaining access to the justice system or of </text>
<text top="169" left="474" width="68" height="12" font="1"><b>challenging </b></text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="293" height="12" font="1"><b>by legal means his arrest and subsequent expulsion</b></text>
<text top="181" left="350" width="192" height="12" font="0">. According to the case file, Mr. Vélez </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Loor lives off selling different kinds of articles as an itinerant trader and he receives no support </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">from his family. It is a matter of record that Mr. Vélez Loor lives in a room which he rents with </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">other people and that he is in declining health. He alleges that his economic situation does not </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">allow him to have the medical treatment that he requires. One day he fainted and one of the </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="340" height="12" font="0">people with whom he rents the room found him lying on the floor.</text>
<text top="241" left="397" width="4" height="8" font="3">9</text>
<text top="242" left="401" width="141" height="12" font="0"> The petitioner alleges that </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Mr. Vélez Loor has received no medical attention since the cruel violations of human rights to </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">which  he  was  subjected  in  Panama.  According  to  his  lawyer,  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  complains  of </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">numerous  ailments  and  there  are  a  number  of  movements  that  he  cannot  make  easily,  for </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">example,  he  cannot  stoop  down  as  the  blood  pressure  in  his  head  hurts  him,  or  turn  to  one </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="321" height="12" font="0">side  when  he  is  lying  down  as  his  spine  causes  him  pain.</text>
<text top="302" left="378" width="8" height="8" font="3">10</text>
<text top="303" left="386" width="156" height="12" font="0">  Moreover,  according  to  the </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">complaint,  the  after-effects  of  the  torture  have  led  to  a  number  of  relapses  which  have </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="333" height="12" font="0">prevented him from carrying out his work as he otherwise would. </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">45. With regard to indigent cases, the Inter-American Court has pointed out that a State that </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">fails to provide free legal advice in cases of indigence may not later argue that a given remedy </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="152" height="12" font="0">was available but not utilized.</text>
<text top="375" left="209" width="8" height="8" font="3">11</text>
<text top="376" left="217" width="324" height="12" font="0"> In particular, the Inter-American Court has pointed out that if </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">an  individual  requires  legal  aid  to  protect  a  right  guaranteed  by  the  Convention  and  his </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">indigence  prevents  him  from  obtaining  it,  he  is  relieved  of  responsibility  for  exhausting </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="100" height="12" font="0">domestic  remedies.</text>
<text top="411" left="157" width="8" height="8" font="3">12</text>
<text top="412" left="165" width="377" height="12" font="0">  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  was  sentenced  in  Panama  to  a  prison  term  for  having </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">repeatedly  entered  Panama  in  an  illegal  fashion.  Due  process  requires  that  someone  against </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">whom charges are made must have the right to defend himself personally or be helped by a </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">defense attorney of his own choosing and if he does not do so he has the inalienable right of </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">being  helped  by  a  defense  lawyer  provided  by  the  State,  whether  or  not  pro  bono  under </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="69" height="12" font="0">domestic law.</text>
<text top="472" left="126" width="8" height="8" font="3">13</text>
<text top="473" left="134" width="407" height="12" font="0"> Given that Mr. Vélez Loor was not Panamanian, it is obvious that he needed to </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">retain  a  Panamanian  lawyer  to  defend  himself  against  the  charges  brought  against  him  in </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="473" height="12" font="0">Panama.  This is  how  the  Convention  guarantees  the  right  to legal  aid in legal  proceedings.</text>
<text top="496" left="531" width="8" height="8" font="3">14</text>
<text top="497" left="539" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Although  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  has  been  provided  with  legal  aid  to  bring  his  case  before  the </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Commission, he was able to document the difficulty he had obtaining legal aid, particularly at </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="388" height="12" font="0">the time of his arrest and throughout the period of his detention in Panama. </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">46.  Consequently,  based  on  the  terms  of  Article  48  of  the  Convention  and  Article  31  of  the </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Rules  of  Procedure,  in  reviewing  the  case,  particularly  taking  into  account  the  fact  that  Mr. </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Vélez  Loor  was  unable  to  exhaust  domestic  remedies  as  he  was  deprived  of  liberty  and  was </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">without legal counsel, the IACHR finds in favor of applying the exception provided for in Article </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">46.2.b  of  the  American  Convention,  given  that  the  party  alleging  violation  of  his  rights  has </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">been  denied  access  to  the  remedies  under  domestic  law  or  has  been  prevented  from </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="92" height="12" font="0">exhausting them. </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>3. </b></text>
<text top="655" left="85" width="160" height="12" font="1"><b>Period for filing the petition </b></text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">47.  In  accordance  with  the  provisions  of  Article  46.1.b  of  the  Convention,  admission  by  the </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Commission  of  a  complaint  shall  be  subject  to  the  following  requirements  –namely,  that  the </text>
<text top="715" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="726" left="57" width="351" height="10" font="5">9 Letter from Mr. José Villagrán, attorney for Mr. Vélez Loor dated November 7, 2005. </text>
<text top="736" left="57" width="13" height="10" font="5">10 </text>
<text top="736" left="70" width="16" height="10" font="7"><i>Ibid</i></text>
<text top="736" left="85" width="6" height="10" font="5">. </text>
<text top="746" left="57" width="78" height="10" font="5">11 I/A Court H.R., </text>
<text top="746" left="136" width="213" height="10" font="7"><i>Exceptions to the Exhaustion of Domestic Remedies</i></text>
<text top="746" left="349" width="193" height="10" font="5"> (Art. 6.1, 46.2.a, and 46.2.b of the American </text>
<text top="756" left="57" width="363" height="10" font="5">Convention on Human Rights). Advisory Opinion OC-11/90 of August 10, 1990, para. 28. </text>
<text top="765" left="57" width="13" height="10" font="5">12 </text>
<text top="765" left="70" width="16" height="10" font="7"><i>Ibid</i></text>
<text top="765" left="85" width="48" height="10" font="5">., para. 31. </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="13" height="10" font="5">13 </text>
<text top="775" left="70" width="16" height="10" font="7"><i>Ibid</i></text>
<text top="775" left="85" width="48" height="10" font="5">., para. 25. </text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="13" height="10" font="5">14 </text>
<text top="785" left="70" width="16" height="10" font="7"><i>Ibid</i></text>
<text top="785" left="85" width="6" height="10" font="5">. </text>
</page>
<page number="10" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="291" width="16" height="12" font="0">10 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petition or communication is lodged within a period of six months from the date on which the </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">party alleging violation of his rights was notified of the final judgment at the national level. The </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="465" height="12" font="0">six-month rule guarantees legal certainty and stability once the decision has been adopted. </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">48.  Under  Article  32.2  of  the  Commission’s  Rules  of  Procedure,  in  those  cases  in  which  the </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">exceptions  to  the  requirement  of  prior  exhaustion  of  domestic  remedies  are  applicable,  the </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petition  shall  be  presented  within  a  reasonable  period  of  time,  as  determined  by  the </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Commission. Under said Article, the Commission &#34;shall consider the date on which the alleged </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="329" height="12" font="0">violation of rights occurred and the circumstances of each case.&#34; </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">49. With regard to the petition to be examined, the Commission has established applicability of </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the exception regarding lack of access to the remedies referred to in Article 46.2.b and must </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">therefore  evaluate  whether  the  petition  was  presented  within  a  reasonable  period  in </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">accordance with the specific circumstances of the case at hand. In this regard, by virtue of the </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">particular  circumstances  in  which  the  petition  was  submitted,  which  include  allegations  of </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">arbitrary detention, mistreatment, and torture, and considering that the petitioner argues that </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">he was not in a position to seek remedies in Panama and had instead to file complaints with </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the Panamanian Embassy in Ecuador (according to the petitioner, in February 2004) and given </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">that  the  State  has  provided  no  details  about  any  criminal  proceedings  undertaken  in </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">connection with these complaints, the Commission finds that the petition under consideration </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="188" height="12" font="0">was filed within a reasonable period. </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>4. </b></text>
<text top="303" left="85" width="248" height="12" font="1"><b>Duplication of procedures and international </b></text>
<text top="303" left="333" width="70" height="12" font="6"><i><b>res judicata </b></i></text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">50. There is no suggestion in the case file that the subject of the petition or communication is </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">pending  in  another  international  proceeding  for  settlement,  nor  that  the  petition  or </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">communication is  substantially  the  same  as  one  previously  studied  by  the  Commission  or  by </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">another international organization. Accordingly, the requirements established in Articles 46.1.c </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="374" height="12" font="0">and 47.d of the American Convention shall be deemed to have been met. </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="14" height="12" font="1"><b>5. </b></text>
<text top="400" left="85" width="207" height="12" font="1"><b>Characterization of the facts alleged </b></text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">51.  For  purposes  of  admissibility,  the  Commission  shall  decide  whether  the  petition  or </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">communication does state facts that tend to establish a violation of the rights guaranteed by </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">this Convention, as stated in Article 47.b of the American Convention, if the statements of the </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner or of the state indicate that the petition or communication is manifestly groundless </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="372" height="12" font="0">or obviously out of order, according to paragraph (c) of the same Article. </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">52.  The  standard  for  assessing  these  criteria  is  different  from  the  standard  required  for </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">deciding  on  the  merits  of  a  complaint.  The  Commission  must  carry  out  a  “prima  facie” </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">assessment  so  as  to  examine  whether  the  complaint  establishes  the  apparent  or  potential </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">violation  of  a  right  that  is  guaranteed  under  the  Convention  and  not  so  as  to  establish  the </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">existence of a violation. Such an examination is a summary analysis that does not imply any </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="235" height="12" font="0">prejudice or preliminary opinion on the merits.</text>
<text top="557" left="292" width="8" height="8" font="3">15</text>
<text top="558" left="300" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">53.  The  Commission  does  not  find  that  the  petition  is  “manifestly  groundless”  or  that  it  is </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="351" height="12" font="0">“obviously out of order”. As a result, the Commission considers that, </text>
<text top="595" left="407" width="56" height="12" font="2"><i>prima facie</i></text>
<text top="595" left="463" width="79" height="12" font="0">, the petitioner </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="257" height="12" font="0">has met the criteria set forth in Article 47.b and c. </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">54. Mr. Vélez Loor was incarcerated pursuant to resolution Nº 7306 dated December 6, 2002 </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">of the National Office of Migration (Dirección Nacional de Migración), which sentenced him to </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">two years in prison, without a trial or even a hearing, on the basis of the provisions of  article </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="231" height="12" font="0">67  of  Decree  law  Nº  16  of  June  20,  1960  (</text>
<text top="668" left="288" width="28" height="12" font="2"><i>supra</i></text>
<text top="668" left="317" width="225" height="12" font="0">  para.  20).  This  Decree  Law  provides  that </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">anyone  who  is  a  recidivist  in  clandestinely  entering  Panama  without  the  appropriate </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">documentation  will  be  sentenced  to  two  years  of  “agricultural  work  in  the  Penal  colony  in </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="450" height="12" font="0">Coiba”  and  will  be  obliged  to  leave  the  country  at  the  end  of  that  period.  On  July  29</text>
<text top="703" left="507" width="7" height="8" font="3">th</text>
<text top="704" left="514" width="29" height="12" font="0">,  the </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">National  Director  of  Migration,  by  means  of  note  Nº  DNMYN-AL-274-03  notified  that  if  Mr. </text>
<text top="728" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Vélez was in possession of the respective ticket or airline ticket to leave Panama, Resolution Nº </text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">736  would  be  rendered  without  effect.  The  Ecuadorian  Embassy  in  Panama,  however, </text>
<text top="764" left="57" width="147" height="11" font="4">                                                 </text>
<text top="775" left="57" width="344" height="10" font="5">15 IACHR, Admissibility Report Nº 21/04, Petition 12.190, José Luís Tapia González </text>
<text top="775" left="401" width="18" height="10" font="7"><i>et al</i></text>
<text top="775" left="419" width="123" height="10" font="5">., (Chile), February 24, 2004, </text>
<text top="785" left="57" width="40" height="10" font="5">para. 33. </text>
</page>
<page number="11" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="291" width="16" height="12" font="0">11 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">maintains that the liberation of Mr. Vélez could not be achieved earlier due to the fact that the </text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Director of Migration had discussed the case by telephone with the consulate and informed it </text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">that  she  would  only  authorize  the  deportation  of  detainees  for  this  kind  of  crime  when  the </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">period of detention had been completed. In fact, however, Mr. Vélez Loor was detained for ten </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">months and was deported back to Ecuador with passage obtained by the Ecuadorian Embassy </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="164" height="12" font="0">through a private businessman. </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">55. The Commission is of the opinion that detention pursuant to Decree Law Nº 16 of June 30, </text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">1960 raises questions of the “arbitrariness of the arrest or detention” of Mr. Vélez Loor, (under </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Article 7.3 of the American Convention, as well as questions regarding Mr. Vélez Loor’s right to </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">challenge the detention and to defend himself against the two year prison term (under Article </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">7.5 and (6)). In addition Mr. Vélez Loor was held in different prisons and not in the detention </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">center at Coiba where he was supposed to perform “agricultural work” pursuant to the Decree </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Law  that  authorized  his  detention.  In  this  context,  the  Commission  also  recognizes  that  the </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">petitioner has alleged a violation of Article 21 in that his property was taken from him when he </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">was  detained  by  the  authorities.  Since  the  State  argues  that  he  had  no  possessions  on  him </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">when he was detained, in the next stage of the proceedings the petitioner will be required to </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="124" height="12" font="0">prove these allegations. </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">56. The fact that this was a situation in which administrative authorities imposed a two year </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">prison  sentence  on  an  “illegal”  or  undocumented  person,  allegedly,  in  transit,  without  the </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">possibility  of  judicial  review,  constitutes  a  possible  violation  of  Article  2  of  the  American </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Convention  regarding  the  responsibility  to  adopt  measures  to  give  effect  to  the  American </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Convention at the national level, Article 8.1 regarding the right to due process and Article 25 </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">regarding access to justice. The petitioner also argues a violation of his right to due process in </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">that  the  law  was  only  a  decree  law  issued  by  the  Executive  and  not  a  law  debated  and </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="331" height="12" font="0">sanctioned by Congress before being approved by the Executive. </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="376" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">57.  In  addition,  the  petitioner  points  out  that  Mr.  Vélez  Loor  was  subjected  to  conditions  of </text>
<text top="388" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">detention  that  were  at  times  accompanied  by  cruel,  inhumane,  and  degrading  treatment, </text>
<text top="400" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">including torture in alleged violation of Article 5 of the American Convention. At the same time, </text>
<text top="412" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">he asserts that he did not have access to legal aid during his detention. Moreover, he states </text>
<text top="424" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">that he did not receive medical attention of the kind necessary to enable him to cope with the </text>
<text top="437" left="57" width="177" height="12" font="0">after-effects of his alleged torture. </text>
<text top="449" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="461" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">58. With regard to the complaint made about alleged torture, the State refers to the reports of </text>
<text top="473" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the Directorate of Migration and Naturalization [and] the Directorate of Prisons so as to point </text>
<text top="485" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">out that the procedures for deportation and the imposition of penalties were in compliance with </text>
<text top="497" left="57" width="44" height="12" font="0">the law. </text>
<text top="510" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="522" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">59. The Inter-American Commission considers that the alleged torture described in the petition </text>
<text top="534" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">and the lack of information about criminal investigations and penalties relating to these facts </text>
<text top="546" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">(denial  of  justice)  constitute  a  possible  violation  of  Articles  5,  8,  and  25  of  the  American </text>
<text top="558" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Convention and Articles 1, 6, and 8  of the  Inter-American Convention to Prevent and  Punish </text>
<text top="570" left="57" width="482" height="12" font="0">Torture. Moreover, the allegations about a lack of suitable medical attention to treat the after-</text>
<text top="583" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">effects of torture amount to a possible  violation of Article 5 (Right to Humane Treatment) of </text>
<text top="595" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">the Convention. At the same time, the Commission will analyze the legal and prison rules that </text>
<text top="607" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">apply  to  undocumented  immigrants  and  the  effect  they  may  have  had  on  the  possible </text>
<text top="619" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">violations of rights which have been alleged in this case. There will be an investigation of the </text>
<text top="631" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">extent  to  which  the  authorities  abided  by  guarantees  relating  to  consular  assistance  and </text>
<text top="643" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">established  procedures  as  a  requirement  for  deportation.  In  conclusion,  all  the  foregoing </text>
<text top="655" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">considerations  will  be  analyzed  in  connection  with  the  obligation  to  respect  and  guarantee </text>
<text top="668" left="57" width="281" height="12" font="0">rights referred to in Articles 1 and 2 of the Convention. </text>
<text top="680" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="692" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">60.  As  regards  a  possible  violation  of  Article  10  of  the  American  Convention,  a  right  to </text>
<text top="704" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">compensation,  if  someone  has  been  sentenced  by  a  final judgment  through  a  miscarriage  of </text>
<text top="716" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">justice, the Commission considers that this provision is not applicable to the situation at hand. </text>
<text top="728" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Mr. Vélez Loor was not subject to a judicial proceeding, but rather was the alleged victim of an </text>
<text top="741" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">administrative  order,  that  permitted  him  no  right  to  participate  in  the  proceedings  nor  to </text>
<text top="753" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">defend  himself.  There  is  no  possible  “miscarriage  of  justice”  since  there  was  no  question  of </text>
<text top="765" left="57" width="238" height="12" font="0">justice being dispensed by a judicial authority. </text>
<text top="777" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
</page>
<page number="12" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="841" width="595">
<text top="795" left="291" width="16" height="12" font="0">12 </text>
<text top="35" left="57" width="15" height="12" font="1"><b>V. </b></text>
<text top="35" left="85" width="86" height="12" font="1"><b>CONCLUSIONS </b></text>
<text top="48" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="60" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">61. Based  on the considerations of fact and law set forth herein, and without prejudging the </text>
<text top="72" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">substantive  merits  of  the  question,  the  Commission  finds  that  the  present  case  meets  the </text>
<text top="84" left="57" width="414" height="12" font="0">requirements for admission as set forth in Article 46 of the American Convention. </text>
<text top="96" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="108" left="57" width="319" height="12" font="1"><b>THE INTER-AMERICAN COMMISSION ON HUMAN RIGHTS</b></text>
<text top="108" left="376" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="121" left="57" width="3" height="12" font="1"><b> </b></text>
<text top="133" left="57" width="54" height="12" font="1"><b>DECIDES:</b></text>
<text top="133" left="111" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="145" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="157" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">1.  To  declare  the  petition  under  consideration  admissible,  under  Articles  1.1,  2,  5,  7,  8,  21, </text>
<text top="169" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">and  25  of  the  American  Convention,  as  well  as  Articles  1,  6,  and  8  of  the  Inter-American </text>
<text top="181" left="57" width="218" height="12" font="0">Convention to Prevent and Punish Torture. </text>
<text top="194" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="206" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">2.  To  declare  the  part  of  the  petition,  alleging  violation  of  Article  10  of  the  American </text>
<text top="218" left="57" width="133" height="12" font="0">Convention, inadmissible. </text>
<text top="230" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="242" left="57" width="287" height="12" font="0">3. To notify the State and the petitioner of this decision. </text>
<text top="254" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="267" left="57" width="271" height="12" font="0">4. To initiate proceedings into the merits of the case. </text>
<text top="279" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="291" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">5.  To  publish  this  decision  and  include  it  in  its  Annual  Report,  to  be  presented  to  the  OAS </text>
<text top="303" left="57" width="97" height="12" font="0">General Assembly. </text>
<text top="315" left="57" width="4" height="12" font="0"> </text>
<text top="327" left="57" width="295" height="12" font="0">Done and signed in the city of Washington, D.C., on the 23</text>
<text top="326" left="351" width="7" height="8" font="3">rd</text>
<text top="327" left="358" width="184" height="12" font="0"> day of the month of October, 2006. </text>
<text top="339" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">(Signed):  Evelio  Fernández  Arévalos,  President;  Paulo  Sérgio  Pinheiro,  First  Vice-President; </text>
<text top="352" left="57" width="485" height="12" font="0">Florentín  Meléndez,  Second  Vice-President;  Freddy  Gutiérrez,  Paolo  G.  Carozza  and  Víctor  E. </text>
<text top="364" left="57" width="148" height="12" font="0">Abramovich, Commissioners. </text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
